<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pneumat-apologia. Or, An apology for the power &amp; liberty of the Spirit as at first to give a being to, so still to give a blessing by his ordinances. In three sermons preacht at Great Budworth, to some persons of honour, and several of the clergy then present to communicate in reference to the late act. By James Livesey, A.M. &amp; vicar of Budworth.</title>
            <author>Livesey, James, 1625-1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48758</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2595</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213711</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826021</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826021</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30413</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48758)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30413)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1797:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pneumat-apologia. Or, An apology for the power &amp; liberty of the Spirit as at first to give a being to, so still to give a blessing by his ordinances. In three sermons preacht at Great Budworth, to some persons of honour, and several of the clergy then present to communicate in reference to the late act. By James Livesey, A.M. &amp; vicar of Budworth.</title>
                  <author>Livesey, James, 1625-1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 184 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by A.M. for Robert Clavel, in Little-Britain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Holy Spirit --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30413:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30413:1"/>
            <p>ΠΝΕΥΜΑΤ-ΑΠΟΛΟΓΙΑ.</p>
            <p>OR, AN APOLOGY FOR THE POWER &amp; LIBERTY OF THE SPIRIT; As at firſt To give a <hi>Being</hi> to, ſo ſtill to give a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> by his <hi>Ordinances.</hi> IN THREE SERMONS PREACHT AT <hi>Great B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DWORTH,</hi> TO Some Perſons of <hi>Honour,</hi> and ſeveral of the <hi>Clergy</hi> then preſent to <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate</hi> in reference to the late ACT.</p>
            <p>By <hi>James Liveſey,</hi> A.M. &amp; Vicar of <hi>Budworth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> in <hi>Little-Britain,</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:30413:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30413:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <list>
                  <item>To the Honourable Sir <hi>George Warburton,</hi> Baronet.</item>
                  <item>Lord of <hi>Budworth Magna, Aſton, Apleton, Sutton, Warburton, Winnington, Marthal, Pulford,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>And his Incomparably Accompliſht &amp; moſt Noble Lady, Madam <hi>Diana Warburton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>And Right Worſhipful, <hi>William Tutchett,</hi> Of <hi>Whitley,</hi>
                     <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                  </item>
                  <item>His Majeſties <hi>High-Sheriff</hi> for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Palatine of <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>And his Vertuous and worthily Honoured Conſort, Madam <hi>Martha Tutchett.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
With the reſt of the Gentry, and others of the Congregation of <hi>Great Budworth.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honourable, Worſhipful, &amp; Worthy Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHat was then (though not affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately enough) preſented to your attentive and judicious ears, is now moſt humbly offered to your diſcerning eyes; the good Spirit of the Lord hand it down into your Hearts, the beſt receptacle of Divine Truths. 'Twas my work to ſuit the
<pb facs="tcp:30413:3"/>Text to that Occaſion, and the Sermons to the Text; yours to ſuit your Attentions to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and His to do us all good, we doing ſo. If any ſhall demand why theſe were then Preached, or are now publiſhed? your Honour can ſatisfie the former, your Worſhip the latter. That I have mounted the Dedication ſo high, to ſo many, (when to every individual a juſt volume had been an incompetent Oblation) this preſumption I muſt anſwer for.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> that great <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarch accepted a preſent of Water from a poor Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer (with a ſmiling countenance) not having need thereof; for may (perhaps) your Generoſity theſe plain, unpoliſhed Sermons from one under ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Obligations to ſerve you. The cenſures of the ignorant I have no reaſon to regard, nor need I fear thoſe of the Learned (who can do much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with their Pens, yet do nothing) for <hi>de Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus non curat invidia.</hi>—The careleſneſs of many who wofully and wilfully ſquander away Sacrament-days without due obſervation, hath awakened my Pen to remind them of the preciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fulneſs of this Ordinance, and of their duties to their never-dying Souls. Who ſees not ſome ſo ſick that they complain they cannot live, and yet ſo ſinful that they dare not die? before another day any of us (the moſt young or ſtrong) may be in another world; though we ſhall live out, yet ſurely we cannot out-live the determin'd time. Theſe ſerious thoughts of Death cannot
<pb facs="tcp:30413:3"/>bring us ſooner to our graves, but they ſhould bring us nearer to our duties, to a more conſtant and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious attendance on this holy Ordinance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, which is the grand deſign of theſe enſuing Pages.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, the Truths in them contain'd are Gods, as ſuch embrace them; the weakneſſes mine, how many ſoever. I have borrowed help from others to erect this feeble Fabrick, but moſt from the Spirit of the Lord, to whoſe gracious conduct in your paſſage to Glory, I ſhall never ceaſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you, beſeeching that my ſervice be not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted my crime.</p>
            <p>The good Lord make you ſhining Lights in that publick Orb in which God and the King have fixt you, and more illuſtrious Patterns of all Graces and Vertues (wherein you now excell) to thoſe you converſe with. This ſhall be the breathing of his Soul, who is, Sirs,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ever obliged Servant, <hi>J.L.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>Aug. <hi>26. 1673.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:30413:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Beſides ſome miſtakes in pointing, and a few literal; the material <hi>Errata</hi> correct thus I pray.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ERRATA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN the Margent, pag. 125. read <hi>Revel.</hi> 5.8. and p. 141. after <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> add <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: p. 146. read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <list>
               <head>In the Book,</head>
               <item>pag. 10. l. 18. r. deſpiſeth.</item>
               <item>pag. 11. l. 7. r. him <hi>for</hi> hmi.</item>
               <item>pag. 15. l. 23. r. pulls <hi>for</hi> puts.</item>
               <item>pag. 80. l. 9. r. ſcan <hi>for</hi> can.</item>
               <item>pag. 102. l. 17. r. might <hi>for</hi> would.</item>
               <item>pag. 104. l. 4. r. Act the latter.</item>
               <item>pag. 110. l. <hi>antap.</hi> r. Him <hi>for</hi> them.</item>
               <item>pag. 163.
<list>
                     <item>lin. <hi>antep.</hi> neglected.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>penult.</hi> obſervation.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>ult.</hi> in things.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>pag. 165. l. 16. r. wills <hi>for</hi> wits.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermons">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30413:4"/>
            <head>THE SPIRIT of the LORD IN Power and at Liberty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">The firſt Sermon, <hi>July</hi> the 13. 1673.</note> to bleſs his own Inſtitutions, with the effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and uſefulneſs of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords-Supper, aſſerted in THREE SERMONS, Preacht On Three Sacrament-days,</head>
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>On Micah 2.7.</bibl> 
                     <hi>O thou that art named the Houſe of Jacob, is the Spirit of the Lord ſtraitned? are theſe his Doings? Do not my words do good to him that walketh uprightly?</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Legi poteſt <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Druſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>MIcah</hi> was one of them we call the ſmall or leſſer Prophets; not becauſe their Propheſies are of leſs authority and majeſty, or excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30413:5"/>(for they were all the dictates of the Spirit of the Lord) but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are more conciſe and of greater brevity than the firſt four.<note place="margin">Ruffin. in Praefat. in Hoſ.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Propheſies (<hi>Calvin</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives) as now extant are but the marrow and quinteſſence of thoſe Sermons by them preacht to the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah:</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and reduced (ſays <hi>Zanchy</hi>) into one volum,<note place="margin">Proleg. in Hoſ.</note> by the care of thoſe pious Princes inſpired of the Lord, left by reaſon of their little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they ſhould be loſt; and this was done for the Churches benefit in thoſe and ſucceeding Ages.</p>
               <p>This Propheſie contains two ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Sermons.</p>
               <p>The former compriſeth the five firſt, and the latter the three laſt Chapters.</p>
               <p>In the former are three things obſervable.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The <hi>Sins</hi> this people ſtood guilty of before God, and they are <hi>ingentia vitia,</hi> mighty ones.</item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:30413:5"/>
                  <item>2. The <hi>Judgments</hi> of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd againſt this people for thoſe ſins; and they are <hi>ingentia ſupplicia,</hi> doleful, dreadful, but moſt juſt and righteous: For he is too good to do his people hurt, and too juſt to do any people wrong: <hi>remunerat ultra condignum, ſed pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit infra,</hi> Ezra 9.13.</item>
                  <item>3. The <hi>Comforts</hi> interſperſed on purpoſe to ſolace and ſupport their hearts who were found faithful in theſe Kingdoms. He foretells (as is obvious to the meaneſt capacity) both the temporal deliverance of <hi>Judah</hi> out of the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity; and the eternal deliverance of the Church to be gathered out of all Nations through the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Meſſiah.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Their Sins are many, ſo were their Judgments; we ſhall menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on three or four, for no more ſtand in our way unto the Text.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Cultum Idolorum inſtitutum in <hi>Bethel,</hi> &amp; <hi>Dan.</hi> Druſ.</note> 1. Their <hi>Idolatry, Chap.</hi> 1.5. this they are branded with; this is the procuring cauſe of the Lords ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30413:6"/>againſt them in this glorious ſeverity.</p>
               <p>The Judgments threatned for this Sin, you ſee in <hi>verſ.</hi> 6, 7. their capital Sinners were in their capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Cities, <hi>Samaria</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> but they were not too great for the great God to bring to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dign puniſhment.<note place="margin"> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Diffluere faciam.</note> 
                  <hi>I will make Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria as an heap of the field; all the graven Images ſhall be beaten or broken to pieces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next this people are ſtigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with are <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quid non Auri ſacra fames.</note> 
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 2.4. <hi>They covet fields and take them by violence, and hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and take them away, &amp;c.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding neither right nor wrong; provided they got it they cared not <hi>Quo jure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quave injuria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How graphically does the Poet deſcribe this monſter ſin?<note place="margin">Phoc.</note> even in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> own terms, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The Judgment denounc'd for this complicate ſin, you ſee 3, 4 5. Their calamity ſhall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30413:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>be extraordinary <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> their deſolation is irrevocably determined, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively and peremptorily declared, <hi>Behold, againſt this Family do I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe an evil, from which ye ſhall not remove your necks, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third ſin is contempt of and oppoſition againſt his Word, his Ordinances and Officers, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6. and which did accent and aggravate the crime, their delight in and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of ſuch falſe Prophets as would ſpeak <hi>Placentia,</hi> and flatter them in their vicious and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous practiſes, <hi>verſ.</hi> the 11th.</p>
               <p>The Text under conſideration is the Lords expoſtulation with this degenerated people for their foremention'd irreverence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. <hi>O thou that art named the Houſe of Jacob, is the ſpirit of the Lord ſtraitned? Are theſe his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? Do not my words do good to him that walketh uprightly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this laſt clauſe two general parts.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Specification of a choice
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30413:7"/>and precious priviledg, <hi>viz.</hi> To have the Word and Ordinances to do one good, this is a mercy of the firſt Magnitude; I know you pray for it as ſuch; you prize it as ſuch; you praiſe him for it as ſuch; you wait this day for it as ſuch: your non-proficiency under the dews and droppings of the Sanctuary you lament as an heavy judgment, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.10, 11. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The qualification of the perſons to whom it appertains,<note place="margin">Privilegia non ſunt amplianda.</note> 
                     <hi>them who walk uprightly;</hi> rare ones indeed, the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, do not ſo; they ſay, <hi>Privilegia ſunt ſtricti juris.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Conſider the form, 'tis Interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative; the matter or ſenſe of this ſentence, 'tis poſitive.</p>
               <p>'Tis a Categorical propoſition; in which,
<list>
                     <item>1. The Subject, or that which is ſpoken of, viz. <hi>my words.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The Predicat; or that which is ſpoken of his words, <hi>they do good.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Do not my words do good?</hi> yea
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30413:7"/>out all ifs or ands they do, to ſuch as are thus qualified <hi>(i.e.) walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In both are four things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Author or Proprietor of them, — <hi>my words.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The ſignal energy and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar efficacy of them, — <hi>do good.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The grand duty required of ſuch who ſhall receive good by them,—<hi>walking.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. The Modification of the duty here expreſſed, —<hi>uprightly.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>A ſhort explanatory muſt ſerve at preſent, and then the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons reſulting hence will be metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically propoſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">O Dicte, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> prius erat, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in foem. Qui diceris ſed non es. <hi>Druſ.</hi> Vos eſtis Iſraelite nomine non re, <hi>Vat.</hi> &amp; <hi>Para us.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>O thou that art named the Houſe of Jacob; i.e.</hi> who art called, but really art not ſo; you are an hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical generation; <hi>Jacob</hi> that good old Patriarch was a man of godly ſimplicity, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.27. a man full of the fire of holy zeal; O the care he had, and the conſcience he made of reforming his Family, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.2, 3. a man of Prayer, a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30413:8"/>great Wreſtler with God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.28. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.4. A great lover of my Word and Ordinances. Were you (as is ſaid of <hi>Nathanael</hi>) Iſraelites in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, in whom there is no guile; Were you good indeed, my words would do you good. But you ſnarle at and quarrel with my Prophets,<note place="margin">Domino per laeſos ſervos fit injuria.</note> becauſe of thoſe Judgments they have denounc'd againſt you; the fault is not in them, nor yet in me; no, 'tis in your ſelves; you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of them unjuſtly, and ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you deal with me injuriouſly, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.16. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Spiritus <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Latine in Maſcul. Hebr. in Foem. Graece in Neut. Commode ſervit per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonae Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae cui nulla ſexus gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſve diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitas tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itur.</note> 
                  <hi>Is the ſpirit of the Lord strait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned?</hi> By the Spirit of the Lord <hi>Grotius</hi> and <hi>Friedlibius</hi> underſtand the patience, longanimity, mercy and goodneſs of the Lord; others (as <hi>Druſius, Paraeus; &amp;c.</hi>) underſtand the Holy Ghoſt;—What? is he ſo contracted? is he reduced to ſuch an exigence, that he cannot inſpire his Prophets? and appoint them how and what to ſpeak unto you? how audacious is your pride and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs?
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30413:8"/>Is it for you to dictate to them what, when and how to propheſie? Dare you attempt to limit the holy Spirit of God?<note place="margin">Quae haec ſuperbia &amp; impietas? <hi>Paraeus</hi> &amp; <hi>Piſcator.</hi>
                  </note> 'tis not for want of fulneſs in him to publiſh or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form good things, that my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets have commiſſion thus to thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der againſt your impieties.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An iſta ſunt opera. <hi>Vatab.</hi> Cogitatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ejus. <hi>Grot.</hi> Num exitio veſtro dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctetur? non ita intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendae ſunt comminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetarum.</note> 
                  <hi>Are theſe his doings?</hi> That is, the way and method of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty in his dealings; and thoſe in which he delights are ways of love and mercy; he draws with the cords of men; is full of can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and ingenuity; if now he ſpeak harſhly and deal ſeverely with you, know this is not his uſual courſe; but only your preſent caſe calls for it. Conſult <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.21. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Do not my words do good, &amp;c. q.d.</hi> Yea, they do: And if you break off your ſins by true un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned repentance, and believe my Prophets; if you will but take care to walk regularly, you ſhall ſurely find the influences of this my Spirit upon your Hearts, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30413:9"/>my Word and Ordinances to work for your good.</p>
               <p>I now proceed to the Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: From the Context take two.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. 'Tis a doleful caſe and matter of ſaddeſt lamentation when a people (by profeſſion Gods) ſtand in oppoſition againſt his Word, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and Officers: Theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulations and preſſing Interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatories import no leſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. God will own and plead the cauſe of his Ordinances and Officers, whoever dares to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or contemn them. Thus he did againſt this people, and thus he will; <hi>Tua cauſa erit mea cauſa,</hi> Luk. 10.16. <hi>He that deſpiſeth them, deſpiſeshim:</hi> They who do ſo ſhall hear from him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O thou that art named.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 3. However men be called or accounted of by themſelvs or others, yet the Lord can eaſily diſcern and will opportunely diſcover what they are indeed: He knows us <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus &amp; in cute, intus &amp; in corde;</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:30413:9"/>Though the heart of man be <hi>(grande profundum)</hi> a great Deep,<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.8.</note> yet he can fathom it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.10. <hi>I the Lord ſearch the heart:</hi> He is a God of Knowledges, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Totus ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> All things are open, naked, anatomized before him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Art named.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 4. The note is this; 'Tis not enough for a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to have a name or to be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good; they muſt be really ſo: It was a cutting queſtion which St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> put to one, <hi>Quid tibi prodest vocari quod non es?</hi> What will it advantage one to have a name to live if he be dead?<note place="margin">See <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> in Joh. 1.47.</note> To paſs for a Saint here, and to be found amongſt Sinners hereafter; to be reputed an Iſraelite indeed, and to be a Gibeonite; to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the Houſe of Jacob (<hi>i.e.</hi> of the Church of God) and to be of the Houſe of Sodom? How ſhall Men and Angels ſtand amazed at the great day, when the ſecrets of all Hearts ſhall be diſcloſed, to ſee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30413:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſome taken up to Heaven who were named the vileſt of ſinners, and others turned into Hell who were reputed choiceſt Saints: A form will do nothing without the power of Godlineſs. There are two things which every man is mainly concern'd to mind.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>(1) To <hi>be</hi> Good.</item>
                  <item>(2) To <hi>appear</hi> ſo.</item>
               </list>
               <p>He that is not ſo is loſt with God, and he that appears not ſo is loſt with men.</p>
               <p>Ones goodneſs if unknown to himſelf will afford him little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; and if unknown to others, it will procure him little credit.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Abbrevia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus. <hi>Druſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Is the Spirit of the Lord straitned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doct. 5. The Spirit of the Lord is not ſo ſtraitned but he knows how to inſpire and inſtruct his Prophets.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 6. The Spirit of the Lord is then ſtraitned, when proud peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple preſume to preſcribe <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate unto his ſervants the Prophets, what and when and to whom they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30413:10"/>ſhall ſpeak, and when and what not. <hi>Are theſe his doings?</hi> Hence note, that</p>
               <p>Doct. 7. The <hi>ordinary</hi> way of the Lords dealing with men is in love and mercy; acts of judgment are his; but they are his ſtrange, not his genuine acts; how full and ſweet is that in <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.8. <hi>How ſhall I give thee up, Ephraim? How ſhall I deliver thee Iſrael, &amp;c.</hi> In this ſacred volum where is the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel? What pathetick Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions puts he there unto himſelf? <hi>q.d.</hi> Thou art upon the brink of deſtruction; 'tis but a giving thee up and thou art ruined. Oh — but how: how ſhall I do it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Do not my words, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 8. Note, that the Word deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and Ordinances diſpenſed by faithful Miniſters are his.—Attend them then with due care and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, with fear and reverence, with faith and patience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 9. From the connexion of the principal efficient and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental cauſes, <hi>viz.</hi> the Spirit and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30413:11"/>the Word: Such as ſincerely deſire to receive good from God, muſt attend to and depend on the Spirit of the Lord in the uſe of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.<note place="margin">Ubi enim Eccleſia ibi &amp; ſpiritus, ubi ſpiritus Dei illic eſt Eccleſia &amp; omnis gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia. <hi>Iren.</hi> lib. <hi>3.</hi> ud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> For the Word can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without the Spirit, and the Spirit will do nothing (ordinarily) without the Word: Let people talk as their deluded fancies prompt them; One day they will ſee and ſay, that they who are enemies to the Word, are no true friends to the Spirit; deſpiſing the one they do quench the other: <hi>Quae Deus conjunxit, &amp;c.</hi> How ſweet, Oh, what a reviving Cordial is that precious promiſe to a pious Soul, in <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.24. In all places where I record my Name (my word and Ordinances, by which I am known, as a man is by his name) I will come unto thee (by my Spirit) and I will bleſs thee; there ſhall be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable meeting and a Cordial cloſing of my Spirit with your Spirits: See one for all, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.20, 21. <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee thy Teachers</hi>—
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30413:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>mark that, <hi>and thine ears ſhall hear a word behind thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Do not my words do good?</hi> There is a twofold word, the one is <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum audibile,</hi> that's the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.17. and there is <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum viſibile,</hi> viz. the Sacraments; they are call'd viſible Sermons: as Chriſt in that conveys himſelf by the ear, ſo in theſe he conveys himſelf by the eye into the Heart. Hence ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 10. That the Word and Ordinances of God are very ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative and powerful. The Spirit of the Lord concurring, they are not only preceptive and directive, but affective and effective; <hi>they are the rod of his ſtrength,</hi> Pſal. 110.2.</p>
               <p>In a word there is a ſevenfold force or power in the Word:</p>
               <p>There is a Sin-ſubduing power, it puts down ſtrong holds, caſts down carnal reaſonings; Oh 'tis mighty through God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5.</p>
               <p>A Soul-humbling power, it lays
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30413:12"/>a proud ſinner as low as Hell; makes him cry out, Lord I am vile: what wilt thou have me to do, and I will do it: To be, and I will endeavour to be it, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.31.</p>
               <p>A Soul-cleanſing power, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.3. <hi>Now are ye clean through the Word which I have ſpoken to you.</hi> And <hi>chap.</hi> 17.17. <hi>Sanctifie them through thy truth, thy word is truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Soul-ſolacing power: This (word of promiſe) is my comfort in my affliction, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.50. it keeps the Soul from fainting; a promiſe like pearl in broth is cordial.</p>
               <p>A Soul-quickening power: No ſuch Incentives to holy duties in the World as in the Word: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.50.</p>
               <p>A Soul-ſearching power: It ranſacks and rifles the Conſcience, and looks into the moſt ſecret tranſactions of the Heart: When the Sun ſhines into the Houſe the Atoms are eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcerned; when the Word ſhines into the Heart our ſecret luſts are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30413:12"/>eaſily diſcovered, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</p>
               <p>A Soul-healing power; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.20. <hi>He ſent his Word and healed them:</hi> How long might a Soul ſit at the foot of a Philoſopher and hear his Lectures of Morality, ere it ſhould experimentally feel and find ſuch an Heart-transforming power going along with them; ſuch a mighty change wrought by them; <hi>Eſt quaedam verbi omnipotentia;</hi> as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid of Prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To him that walketh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>11</label> 
                  <hi>D.</hi> 11. Chriſtianity is a walk; a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians life is not a ſtanding or ſitting ſtill: every day muſt we do a days work, and go a days journey to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Heavenly Country.</p>
               <p>Up then and be doing, here is not your reſt, <hi>Quo brevior opportunitas, co major ſedulitas;</hi> loſe your ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and you may loſe your Souls; opportunities are for Eternity but they are not to Eternity: The Spirit will not always ſtrive with man; now Chriſt ſtands and knocks,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.3. Cant. 5.3.</note>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:30413:13"/>but he that ſtands ſtays not; give him no childiſh, no churliſh an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers; work and walk now; now if ever, now for ever; you may want an
<list>
                     <item>(1) opportunity, if you ſlip this;<note place="margin">Eſto in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebus aeſtatis Formica. <hi>Prov. Arab.</hi>
                        </note> who knows what a day may bring forth? if you be not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in duty, God may be preſent in judgment; may come quickly, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.5. His Judgments are often ſudden and prevent mens expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but never their deſerts: <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.15. Ere you can get out of bed he may let out your blood. Or</item>
                     <item>(2) you may want ability and not be in a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity; a ſickneſs may come that may take away your ſenſes, your friends perhaps may be forc'd to bind you in your beds; and is that a ſeaſon for the greateſt work of all, which is not fit for any work at all? Shall the beſt Maſter be the laſt, the leaſt, the worſt ſerved?</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Why ſhould our vain hopes of living long, remit or abate our
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:30413:13"/>cares of living well, and working hard? Moſt never think of going faſter till they are forc'd to think they ſhall not go much longer. Let us mind our way and mend our pace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doctr.</hi> 12. 'Tis an impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant duty which concerns us all to walk uprightly, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1.</p>
               <p>And 'tis the priviledg of ſuch to have the word of the Lord to work for their good: <hi>They ſhall not hear in vain: Their ſouls ſhall live,</hi> Iſa. 55.3.</p>
               <p>But the propoſition on which I purpoſe now to fix (waving all the reſt) is this, and it takes moſt of them in.</p>
               <p>Doct. <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord is not ſo ſtraitned but that he can cauſe his Word and Ordinances to do them good who walk uprightly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> writing three Books to <hi>Gratian</hi> the Emperour concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Spirit of the Lord, fronts his firſt with this paſſage, Sp. S. <hi>non aut alienae poteſtati eſt ſubjectus,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30413:14"/>aut juri; ſed ſuae libertatis arbiter, omnia pro authoritate propriae vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatis, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are three great Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>(1) The Miniſtry of the Word.</item>
                  <item>(2) Baptiſm.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And the Lords Supper is the third.</p>
               <p>The firſt we have diſpatcht, and in our laſt diſcourſe the ſecond was finiſh'd too; to refreſh your Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, give me favour to hint the heads thereof, or ſome few on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and them briefly.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Ad templu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dei perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vuli ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficati Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramento Chriſti, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generati ſpiritu ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto, qui cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tè per aeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum poſſunt cognoſcere Deum. <hi>Aug. Epiſt. 57. Darda. cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca Med.</hi>
                  </note>(1) It was proved by Scripture, that the Infants of Chriſtian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents (viſible Profeſſors) are true Denizons of the viſible Church and Kingdom of God; and have a juſt right to and intereſt in Gods <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> or Covenant of Grace.</p>
               <p>That the truth of Grace in the Parents is not the rule we are to act by in admitting Infants to this Ordinance. Surely he would never
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:30413:14"/>make that the condition upon which his Miniſters muſt apply this his Ordinance, which none but God himſelf can infallibly know; let Parents be what they will (vicious and ſcandalous) if the Church caſt not them out, we muſt not caſt theirs out. A viſible profeſſion of Faith and Holineſs in the Parents, (though there be not a converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion congruous to that profeſſion) intitles the Child to Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>That Infants are capable of the Spirit of the Lord, of ſaving Grace, of Union with Chriſt, of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, of pardon of Sin, all which are ſealed in Baptiſm; if any deny this, they muſt then ſay, either, That theſe are not neceſſary unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; or, That no Child dying in his Infancy can be ſaved: Both which are abſurd enough.</p>
               <p>That if Infants have no right to this Seal of the Covenant, their condition under the Goſpel is much worſe, and their priviledges leſs than were thoſe of Jewiſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:30413:15"/>under the Law; theirs had one, <hi>viz.</hi> Circumciſion; ours none.</p>
               <p>That the Commandment for Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion being ſo expreſs, plain and legible in the Old Teſtament, there is no more need of a new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment for Infant-Baptiſm in the New, than for a new Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the holy Obſervation of the Lords-day.</p>
               <p>That the Covenant (and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Commandment) was then the principal ground and reaſon of Circumciſion (and is now of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.) Circumciſion was called the Covenant, and not the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and the contempt or viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it was call'd the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Covenant, not of the Commandment;<note place="margin">Vide Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takerum contra Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeum fuſius hâc de re <hi>pag. 681. 682.</hi>
                  </note> and the deſpiſers were threatned to be cut off for the violation of the Covenant, not of the Commandment, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10, 13.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly circumciſed, as well as <hi>Iſaac.</hi> No Scripture rule was tranſgreſſed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30413:15"/>when <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> when <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed; yet what they were, you know, the whole multitude of the Iſraelites were baptized, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 2. Yet were not all true Believers, <hi>verſ.</hi> the 5.</p>
               <p>That we cannot infallibly know, but only charitably judg who are true Believers; and that, Though Infants cannot lay hold on Chriſt by the hand of Faith, yet he can and will embrace them in the arms of his love, and bleſs them.</p>
               <p>That he whoſe child was uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed (by his neglect) was in Gods account uncircumcis'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48. 'tis ſo in this caſe of Baptiſm; and if uncircumciſed, he was not admitted to the Paſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; no nor into the Sanctuary, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.9.</p>
               <p>That the enemies of Infant-bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm deal not ingenuouſly in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring from us an expreſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment for our practice, whilſt mandment for our practice, whilſt they cannot produce one for theirs.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30413:16"/>Where is your command to keep the Infants of viſible profeſſors from this ordinance till they be ſix, ten, or twenty years of age, or till they can make profeſſion of their Faith?</p>
               <p>Or where is your command to baptize Children when grown up? if you inſiſt upon example, then where is your example for your admitting of Women to the Lords Supper? But of this more the laſt time.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Antiquity of this Ordinance was vindicated from the imputation of Novelty;<note place="margin">Nullus eſt Scriptor tam vetuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, qui ejus origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ad A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolorum ſeculum pro certo non refert. <hi>Calvin.</hi>
                  </note> and that aſſertion of Judicious <hi>Calvin</hi> in his <hi>Inſtit. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. <hi>ſect.</hi> 8. and of learned <hi>Zanchy</hi> in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 226 <hi>page,</hi> was conſidered and confirmed by the concurrent Teſtimonies of the Ancients in the ſeveral Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; as of <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Irenaeus, Origen, Cyprian, Ambroſe, Auſtin, Nazianzen, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, The high and noble ends for which it was inſtituted.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30413:16"/>The great uſefulneſs and advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of it was ſhewed; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to thoſe who are of maturer age, but even to Infants (Elect ones, I mean) ordinarily, when they are baptized: As the Spirit moving upon the waters produc'd a world, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. and brought forth living Creatures; ſo the Spirit mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving upon the Soul can produce the ſeeds of Grace in it: Conſult at better leiſure the 27th. Article of Religion, and you will find it cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſponding with the judgment of the Fathers, with the moſt eminent Divines of theſe latter ages, with the Holy Scriptures, which is <hi>inſtar omnium.</hi> All which aſſert the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Infants, ordinarily in the act of Adminiſtration; to clear this (perhaps a more important truth than many in this Age are appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of) I refer you to what an eminent Doctor of our Church hath left up record, <hi>D.C.B</hi>'s Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Regeneration: It ſhall ſuffice
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30413:17"/>now to mention only four or five. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> calls Baptiſm our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation Chriſt, 1 <hi>Homil.</hi> in <hi>Act.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: In Baptiſm the chief part is the ſpirit, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> by which the water becomes effectual.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baſil</hi> in anſwer to that queſtion, <hi>How are Chriſtians ſaved?</hi> makes this return, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: by being regenerated by the grace received in Baptiſm: <hi>de ſp. ſ. cap.</hi> 10. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Baptiſm is unto me the beginning of life.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> is for it,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ep.</hi> 23.</note> and <hi>Auſtin</hi> too; ſee his Epiſtle to <hi>Bomface</hi> (a noble Earl) on this Argument, and to <hi>Daranus,</hi> Ep. 57.—<hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta in ſolis electis, &amp;c.</hi> The Sacraments do work that which they ſignifie only in the Elect;<note place="margin">Zanchy lib. Confeſſ. cap. de Bapt. P. Martyr loc. com. claſſ. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi> ſect. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> that is quoted by <hi>P. Lombard</hi> in Sent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Chamier</hi> thoſe two great Lights of <hi>France</hi> are full for this too; though in their Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion Infants could not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30413:17"/>what that ſign meant, yet they were truly circumciſed unto the mortification of their depraved and defiled nature, which when at maturity they meditated on. <hi>Inſtit. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. <hi>ſect.</hi> 20. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi plura ad propoſitum.</hi> See alſo <hi>cap.</hi> 15. <hi>ſ.</hi> 12. And <hi>Chamier, de ſacr. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>p</hi> 4. <hi>Tantum abeſt,</hi> &amp;c. 'Tis ſo far from us that we ſhould teach that Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm effecteth nothing upon Infants till they come to age; that on the contrary we know that the effect of Baptiſm which is perform'd im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately by the Spirit himſelf, ſometimes goes before the very ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of Baptiſm; therefore we ſay, that either then there is ſome effect in truth and indeed when the Sacrament is adminiſtred, <hi>aut nullum unquam futurum;</hi> or elſe there will never be any at all; that is, then our ſins are truly remitted, and our Adoption made ſure to us, but all this morally; with them concur our own Chieftains, <hi>Jewel, Ward, Davenant, Bucer, Ames,</hi> and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30413:18"/>
                  <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> the laſt in his cenſure of a Dialogue of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> urgeth this argument amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>pag.</hi> 40. <hi>to</hi> 46.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>They to whom God giveth the ſign and ſeal of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by Faith and of Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they have Faith and Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, for God giveth no lying ſign, he ſealeth no vain or falſe Covenants.</p>
                  <p>But God gave to Infants Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion which was the ſign and ſeal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith and Regeneration, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.11.</p>
                  <p>Therefore Infants had (and conſequently now have) Faith and Regeneration, though not in the crop or harveſt, yet in the bud and beginning of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Graces.</p>
               </q>
               <p>A little after: <q>They that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny this reaſon muſt either make God the Author of a lying ſign and ſeal of the Covenant to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and his Infants; or they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:30413:18"/>muſt hold that Infants had thoſe graces then, but not now; both which are wicked and abſurd; or they muſt ſay, Circumciſion was not the ſign and ſeal of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs which is by faith, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, And in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſome rules were hinted'; I ſhall only ſuperadd one more now; mark it well pray. If you would have the bleſſing of the Lord upon this initiating, matriculating Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, act regularly, I mean ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule of the Word: What's that you'l ſay? I anſwer let them be baptized
<list>
                     <item>1. Early.</item>
                     <item>2. Publickly.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">(1) Early: <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the Faithful delayed not the Circumciſion of his dear <hi>Iſaac</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the eighth day; and that was a painful ordinance. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> well obſerves that the Sacraments of the New Teſtament are
<list>
                     <item>1. Fewer in Number.</item>
                     <item>2. Clearer in Signification.</item>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:30413:19"/>
                     <item>3. Eaſier in Obſervation.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Who dare ſay of this or that particular infant, it is not rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate? and Mr. <hi>Tombs</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth ſuch are to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Joh. 7.22, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>John</hi> was circumciſed the eighth day, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.59. So was Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.21. That he was not baptized till about thirty years old, was becauſe till about that time <hi>John</hi> baptized none.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> did circumciſe the Children which they bought with their moneys, the ſame day they bought them; though it was the very day they were born; yea, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the eighth day fell to be the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, yet the <hi>Jews</hi> circumcis'd the Child therein, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.22. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Canon: Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion in the time thereof drives away the Sabbath:<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Ainſw.</hi> on Gen. 17.12. <hi>Maimonid.</hi> his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <hi>ch.</hi> 1. <hi>ſect.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>(i e.)</hi> A man muſt omit the Sabbath (the keeping of it) for to circumciſe in due time. Was the Lord ſo angry with <hi>Moſes</hi> for the not circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his child in due time, that he ſought to kill him in the Inn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.24. and is he well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with your delays? St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> judgment is well known in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:30413:19"/>caſe,<note place="margin">Tanto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis pro par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulis loqui debemus, quanto ipſi pro ſe loqui non poſſunt. <hi>Aug. Ep. 89.</hi> juxla med.</note> 
                  <hi>Non est justum</hi> (ſpeaking of Baptiſm) <hi>ut res quae tam magna, tam praeclara creditur, negligenter aut tardius quam expedit, requiratur.</hi> It is not juſt that a matter of ſuch moment and importance ſhould be negligently and ſlowly gone about; can you devote and dedicate your Children to God too ſoon? Can you ſeal them too early? The ſooner the better they are ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſecrated to the Lord, and have his name put upon them: Is it not a great and choice privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, that our Children have a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſtanding in the Church? can they be too early initiated into the Church or too ſoon engaged to ſerve the Lord? <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.3.</p>
               <p n="2">(2) Publickly: This is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ordinary common rule of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Zepper de Pol. Eccleſ. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> and the Liturgy of the Church. Baptiſm is a publick ſeal of the Covenant of Grace, and therefore ſhould be done publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. You honour God moſt when you ſolemnly and publickly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30413:20"/>and dedicate your little one<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to God.</p>
               <p>You honour this ordinance moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by a publick owning and uſing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it; and we ſhould preſerve the honour of his Inſtitutions all we can; never more need.</p>
               <p>Your little ones are moſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taged this way, they have the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the whole Aſſembly; and by the ſolemnity of this Ordinance your ſelves are more quickned in remembring and renewing your Covenant with God on this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: So much is ſaid (and ſo ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally) by a learned Pen,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Samuel Langley</hi>'s Suſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on review<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> that I cannot preſume to add thereto. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that for the future what is amiſs amongſt us may be redreſſed; let the honour of God be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted, and not the humours of men.</p>
               <p>When Chriſt was baptized he ſent not for <hi>John</hi> to come to him, but himſelf went to <hi>John,</hi> and was bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed publickly, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.13, 16. He hath left us his own example, let none think himſelf too good or too great
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:30413:20"/>to follow his ſteps.</p>
               <p>But becauſe of this preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion the reſt of this diſcourſe ſhall be confined to the third Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, <hi>viz.</hi> The Lords Supper: The Doctrine's this;</p>
               <p>Doct. <hi>The Spirit of the Lord is not ſo ſtraitned, but he can cauſe this. Ordinance to work for their good who walk uprightly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In proſecution of this Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I ſhall reſolve but only eight Queries, very ſuccinctly. For brevity is good,</p>
               <p>Whether it be or be not underſtood.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 Q. <hi>What does this term or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion</hi> [Walk] <hi>import and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Q. What is it to</hi> walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly? —<hi>How is it to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Q. Of what importance and concernment is it, that we walk thus?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 Q. <hi>When does this Ordinance
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:30413:21"/>work for their good who</hi> thus walk?</item>
                  <item>5 Q. <hi>How does it appear that the Spirit of the Lord can do them good by it, who</hi> thus walk?</item>
                  <item>6 Q. <hi>What courſe must a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian take that the Spirit of the Lord may do him good by this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7 Q. <hi>What must one do who hath found good at and by this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, from the powerful workings of the Spirit of the Lord?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8 <hi>Q. What Soul-reviving com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts doth the conſideration of this important. Truth afford to ſuch as conſcientiouſly endeavour to walk uprightly?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Of theſe in order:</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Q. What doth this expreſſion import or intimate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To clear the notion, know, that <hi>walking,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. 'Tis <hi>motus vitalis,</hi> the reſult of a living principle in the Soul:<note place="margin">Actio ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam.</note> Angels do not animate thoſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:30413:21"/>which they aſſume, and their operations therefore are not vital: to ſpeak properly, thoſe Bodies are rather <hi>moved</hi> than <hi>move.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed we read in <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.8. of their eating with <hi>Abraham;</hi> and this is a vital act: but you are not to underſtand it properly but meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorically, they ſeem'd to eat: <hi>At non comederunt actione vitali</hi> (ſays <hi>Mercer</hi>) <hi>ſed cibo in corpus aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum tranſmiſſo, &amp; in aerem tenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſimum reſoluto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There muſt be a vital princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of grace in the Heart, or we cannot walk in Heavens way: <hi>Dum deest aliquid intus;</hi> we are becalm'd and cannot move at all.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis <hi>Motus progreſſivus;</hi> a go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forward: No man ever did or ſhall go to Heaven backward, or get thither by ſtanding ſtill. Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar motion is the motion of the Heavens, but 'tis not the moſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly motion,—We muſt go <hi>from strength to strength,</hi> Pſal. 84.7.</p>
               <p n="3">3. 'Tis <hi>Actus repetitus;</hi> walking
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30413:22"/>implys frequent acts, or a courſe of life; as every act of Godlineſs is a ſtep, ſo the whole of our Actions is our Walk.—And,</p>
               <p n="4">4. 'Tis <hi>Motus ſpontaneus;</hi> a free voluntary motion, not of force but of choice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.30. <hi>I have choſen the way of Truth;</hi> a way that never deceived any, nor will me, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>I have carefully ſought out and choſen 'em.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. 'Tis <hi>Motus arduus;</hi> this walking is all up the hill, againſt winds and waves, and many oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions:—<hi>Hic labor, hoc opus est,</hi> (the way to Hell is all down-hill.) Walking is painful yet the moſt gainful motion. An Heathen Poet could ſay,</p>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>—</q>
               <p n="6">6. 'Tis <hi>Motus ordinatus;</hi> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and well-ordered motion, not a running at random, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedly, but an acting by rule; <hi>i.e.</hi> by the Word,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.9. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. <hi>As many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s walk according to this Rule.—Pſal.</hi> 50.23. A Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:30413:22"/>ordered in all things calls for a Converſation ſuitable.</p>
               <p n="7">7. 'Tis <hi>Motus aequabilis;</hi> an even uniform motion; not now and then, or (as we ſay) by fits and ſtarts.</p>
               <p n="8">8. 'Tis <hi>Motus aeternus;</hi> this wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king (I mean) muſt be even to the end, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.12. 'Tis not enough to ſet out, we muſt alſo hold out, or all our labour is loſt, and our walking is to no purpoſe.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.21.</note> 
                  <hi>It had been better for them</hi> (ſays <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>not to have known the way of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, than after they have known it, to turn from the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> turn our feet into his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, this is a bleſſed turn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed;<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.59. Pſal. 9.17.</note> this will ſerve our turn to bring us to Heaven. Firſt God turns us, and then takes us to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: But to fall off and to turn from God and his way will undo us for ever.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Q. What is it to walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly?
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:30413:23"/>what does this import? how is it to be understood?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſhort thus:</p>
               <p>There is a threefold Upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; <hi>Legal, Moral,</hi> and <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Legal; Adam</hi> in this ſenſe was ſo whilſt he continued in that ſtate of Innocency; his Knowledg of God was clear; his Engagements to God were great; his Enjoyment of God was full; his Communion with God was ſweet; no ſtain at all upon his Nature; his Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Divine Will was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly quadrate and perfect for a time: his Heart and Life did agree with the Law of God exactly, as a well-made Dial goes with the Sun. Thus the Text is not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, for thus can no man walk: He that ſaith, he hath no ſin doth ſin even in ſaying ſo. There are but a few men againſt whom Chriſt hath but a few things; and there is none on Earth againſt whom he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30413:23"/>hath nothing, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.19, 20. As in the worſt there is ſomething good, ſo in the beſt there is ſomething bad. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the Saints, ſaith, <hi>That in them the fleſh lusteth againſt the ſpirit,</hi> Gal. 5.17. Whilſt the Fleſh luſteth, and Satan temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and the World allureth, think it not ſtrange if the precious Sons of <hi>Zion</hi> be now and then found halting, ſometimes taken tripping.</p>
               <p>To have nothing <hi>of Fleſh</hi> is the glorious priviledg of the Saints in Heaven; to have nothing <hi>but fleſh</hi> is the doleful ſtate of the Damned in Hell, To have ſomething of Fleſh and ſomething of Spirit is the caſe of the Saints on Earth. 'Tis the pleaſure of the All-wiſe God it ſhall be thus with us; were it not for ſin Chriſt would not be ſo ſweet unto us as now he is; were it not for Chriſt ſin would not be ſo bitter to us as now it is.—To be freed from all ſin would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce more to our peace, but leſs to Gods honour; leſs to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:30413:24"/>of his wiſdom, power, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2ly.</hi> There is a <hi>Moral upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> thus are they ſaid to be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right who are adorned with Moral vertues, and who walk juſtly, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately, prudently; ſuch was <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stides</hi> and other of the Heathens; this is a fine flower, but you may find it in the wild and waſte of Nature. God becomes Compurga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor for <hi>Abimelech,</hi> That <hi>what he did in taking Sarah, was in the uprightneſs of his heart,</hi> Gen. 20.6. <hi>I know</hi> (ſays God) <hi>that thou didst this in the ſincerity of thy heart; Simplici ac ſincero animo. Joab,</hi> though a man of bloods, yet dealt very uprightly with the King con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the rendition of <hi>Rabah.</hi> Some advance this Moral upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſet it too high, others ſet it too low; 'tis very good, but it does others more good in this World than our ſelves in the other. Of this I do not underſtand the Text neither.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:30413:24"/>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3ly. Evangelical;</hi> This is a Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel that none wears but Chriſts Spouſe; a Grace (if I may ſo call it) that none is graced with but Gods Child; a plant that only grows in Gods Garden; 'tis called godly ſincerity, becauſe it is of God, it aims at God, and ends in God; thus holy <hi>David</hi> reſolv'd to walk, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.2. <hi>I will walk with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my houſe with a perfect heart</hi> thus <hi>Abraham</hi> is commanded to walk, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> triumphs in this, that he had (through Grace) thus walkt; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing is this, the teſtimony of our Conſcience, that in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity we have had our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation in the world.</hi>—In an Evangelical ſenſe one may walk perfectly, and thus <hi>Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did: See <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.6. <hi>They walked in all the Commandments of the Lord blameleſs;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>not ſinleſs,</hi> but blameleſs, <hi>Sine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>querela, non ſine peccato,</hi> as St. <hi>Austin</hi> gloſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it in the end of his 95. <hi>Epiſt.</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:30413:25"/>and ſince him <hi>Oſiander</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>'Tis a true ſaying of one:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>They err egregiouſly who look for that in the Law which is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be found in the Goſpel; for that in themſelves which is only to be found in Chriſt; and for that on Earth which is only to be had in Heaven: <hi>i.e.</hi> A ſinleſs perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</q>
               </p>
               <p>To diſpatch this enquiry, know that to this upright walking three things are neceſſary.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. A Rule is requiſite; a certain, infallible, and inflexible Rule by which we act, that's the Word; 'tis not only a rule of Knowledg but alſo a rule of Duty.</item>
                  <item>2. A knowledg of this Rule, and then there muſt be,</item>
                  <item>3. An acting conformably, ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to our knowledg.</item>
               </list>
               <p>We muſt have an eye as well to the manner of our Obedience as to the matter of our Obedience: For (as <hi>Luther</hi> well) <hi>Adverbia apud De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um praevalent verbis.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:30413:25"/>
               <p>We muſt obey him as well in the ſpirit of the command as in the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it: In thoſe things which ſeem to make againſt us as in thoſe that make for us, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.1, to the 12. <hi>v.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We muſt not only not do that which is evil, but we muſt do that which is good:—We muſt have reſpect to all his Commandments, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6. As good to none at all as not to all; <hi>David</hi> fulfilled all Gods wills, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.22. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Q. We ſhall now enquire after the</hi> Quae ratio, <hi>of what importance and concernment is it that we thus walk?</hi> —</p>
               <p>It were eaſie to be voluminous; but take hints:</p>
               <p>That there is an abſolute and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſable neceſſity of walking ſincerely, uprightly; that it is of great concernment we do ſo; Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. If we appeal to God under
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:30413:26"/>the Law, there we ſee the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. <hi>I am the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, walk before me and be thou perfect or upright.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. If we appeal to Chriſt under the Goſpel, all his commands breathe Holineſs and Uprightneſs; and his promiſes are to the pure and ſincere in Heart, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.8. He came to ſave us, not in our ſin, nor with our ſin, but from our ſin. He requires us to be holy as he is holy; and we muſt follow the example of his life if we hope to be ſaved by the Merits of his Death.</item>
                  <item>3. If we appeal to the practiſe of the Saints under both Diſpenſations, they ever made it their buſineſs to walk uprightly; <hi>Enoch,</hi> and <hi>Noah,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Joſiah,</hi> and <hi>Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah.</hi> Hear one for all, <hi>Remember now O Lord, I beſeech thee, how I have walked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart,</hi> ſays good <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> Iſa. 38.3. For the New Teſtament, conſult 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. and 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Ye are witneſſes, and God alſo, how
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:30413:26"/>holily and justly, and unblameably we behaved our ſelves among you that believe:</hi> —Phil. 1.27.</item>
                  <item>4. If we appeal to Conſcience, our own or others; Conſcience is a faculty or habit of the practical underſtanding, whereby the mind of man by the diſcourſe of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, applys the light it hath to every particular moral act.</item>
               </list>
               <p>There is a Conſcience convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and awakened, but not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted nor renewed: Conſult this and it will tell you that 'tis a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of importance to walk upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; a Conſcience upon the rack will confeſs it freely.</p>
               <p>There is a good renewed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and this will tell you there is a neceſſity of walking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly. In every man God hath placed a Conſcience, 'tis his boſom-preacher, 'tis a petty God, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it reproves, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes, checks and ſmites when we do evil. Ask your Conſciences when you are under ſome ſore af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:30413:27"/>or when upon your Death beds, and they will bear witneſs to this truth; that 'tis your part and prudence, your duty and diſcretion to be in the fear of the Lord all the day long; To walk humbly and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly before God. Excellent is that paſſage of <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> in his Defenſe for the Chriſtians to <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus Pius:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If any be found who lives not as Chriſt hath taught, 'tis a certain Argument he is not a <hi>Christian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> though with the Tongue he confeſs the Doctrine of Chriſt; for not thoſe which only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, but thoſe who make good their profeſſion, doth Chriſt aſſure of Salvation.</p>
               <p>But to ground the Point.</p>
               <p>We are thus oblig'd to walk upon a ſevenfold account.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He is an upright <hi>God</hi> whom we walk <hi>before;</hi> he is ſo in his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in his Attributes, in his Mercy, Love and Juſtice, in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, in his Promiſes, in Threats;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:30413:27"/>he is ſo in his offers and tenders of Chriſt and Grace, and of Pardon, and eternal Salvation; in Him is no iniquity, no hypocriſie at all: He is a God of Truth, his eye is fixt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, his heart is in love with it. He diſguſts and abhors all leaven of hypocriſie, and vizors of piety, all falſeneſs: 'Tis not all you can ſay, or do, or ſuffer or loſe, that can make you precious in his eyes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this ſincerity. In that Pſalm of Thankſgiving there is an excellent paſſage, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.22, to the 28. <hi>I have kept the ways of the Lord.</hi>— <hi>All his judgments are before me, I was alſo upright before him.</hi>—<hi>For with the upright man thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf upright. David</hi> walkt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an upright God, and it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd him the more to walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We have an upright <hi>Pattern,</hi> and upright <hi>Preſidents</hi> to walk <hi>after.</hi> —The Lord Jeſus is our pattern; <hi>he hath left us an example,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.21.</note> 
                  <hi>and we muſt follow his ſteps; who did no ſin,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:30413:28"/>neither was guile found in his mouth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> We muſt look at Jeſus,</hi> Heb. 12.2. He was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a pattern;</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for patience in death, but for holineſs and uprightneſs of life too; for this end and purpoſe is his life recorded in this ſacred Volume,<note place="margin">Bonos tibi adjunge, quia ſi ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius fueris converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis eris &amp; virtutis. <hi>Ambr.</hi>
                  </note> that all his Members might lay it as a golden Samplar before them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which they ſhould work.</p>
               <p>Upright <hi>Preſidents;</hi> the godly Patriarchs, the holy Prophets and Apoſtles, pious Princes, and other religious perſons of whom we read in Holy Story: Theſe are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Examples propounded for all our imitation: In every Profeſſion there are Chieftains.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Roman</hi> Warriors had their <hi>Camilli, Fabricii,</hi> and <hi>Scipio's.</hi> The Philoſophers had their <hi>Plato, Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> and <hi>Pythagoras:</hi> We have the Prophets and Apoſtles. Man is a ductile creature, led as well by the eye as by the ear; we muſt follow them ſo far as they follow
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:30413:28"/>Chriſt.<note place="margin">Non caden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di exemplu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> propoſitum eſt; ſed ſi ceciderie reſurgendi; non ſit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectatio mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus majoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Aug.</hi> in <hi>Pſal. 51.</hi>
                  </note> Their failings indeed are recorded, but for our caution, not for our imitation; their errors are ſet up not as Stars to guide us, but as Rocks to warn us; not as Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks to go by, but as Sea-marks to ſhun by. <hi>Sit caſus majorum timor minorum. Aliorum perditio tua ſit cautio.</hi> Excellent is that of Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> Lib. 4. Ep. pag. 127. <hi>In omnibus actibus tuis imitare bonos, aemulare ſanctos; habeto ante oculos eorum exempla,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We have an upright <hi>Rule</hi> to walk <hi>by,</hi> the Word of God; 'tis that ſhould guide us here; by that we ſhall be judged hereafter.— This is a perfect Rule, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17. an upright and holy Rule; ſo is not the Light within; and as for the Spirit, he is our guide, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14. not our Rule.—Again,</p>
               <p n="4">4. We have an upright <hi>way</hi> to walk in, the way of his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; this is an underfiled and an undefiling way; a pure, and holy, and perfect, and pleaſant way; paths
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:30413:29"/>of life, and peace, and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, all which call for Uprightneſs. <hi>Si vis eſſe beatus, eſto in via imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatus,</hi> Aug. <hi>in</hi> Pſal. 119.1.</p>
               <p n="5">5. We have upright <hi>Companions</hi> to walk <hi>with;</hi> indeed the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are not ſo; the moſt do walk in crooked paths, but in all ages there are ſome who are undefiled in the way, whoſe Hearts are ſound in Gods ſtatutes, and follow the Lord fully, and keep themſelves from their iniquities; ſee St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his Epiſtle to <hi>Florianus, ubi ſupra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. We have an upright, a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect account to give of our walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and workings: Though now we live as if we had no God to ſerve, no Souls to ſave, no accounts at all to give; yet ſurely we ſhall be call'd upon anon to give account of all, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.2. We read of the Counſel which <hi>Alcibiades</hi> gave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Pericles,</hi> whom going to viſit he found buſied about his accounts, <hi>Why doſt thou trouble thy ſelf</hi> (ſays he) <hi>in ſeeking to make thy accounts,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:30413:29"/>rather think of ſome courſe to free thee from making any account at all.</hi> Doubtleſs there are who do thus; but the greater ſorrow and ſhame ſhall they have at the laſt day. Does not the due conſideration hereof lay a mighty obligation on us to walk uprightly? Nothing had ſo great an influence on St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> to recall him from, and to recover him out of his ſinful ways, and to engage him to live an holy and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right life as <hi>(Metus mortis &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremi judicii),</hi> the fear of Death, and the day of Judgment. O that we were wiſe, then would we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member our latter end.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The Reward we ſhall receive will be an upright, juſt and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect reward: <hi>Verily there is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for the Righteous:</hi> A <hi>ſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> Prov. 11.18. <hi>A full reward.</hi> 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. <hi>An everlaſting reward.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. <hi>It ſhall be well with the righteous; their labour ſhall not be in vain in the Lord.</hi> He is not behind with them now, nor will
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:30413:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>he then. They ſhall have Pleaſures without pain; Treaſures without traſh; Riches without ruſt; Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours without envy; Crowns with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cares; and Life without death. If the conſideration of theſe things prevail not with us thus to walk, what ſhall? If they have no influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon us, what will?</p>
               <p>Having premiſed theſe things, the fourth Query comes next in order to be diſcuſſed; go along with me and it ſhall be fully reſolved.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Q. When does this Ordinance of the Supper work for their good who thus walk?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An account hereof take in the Twelve following particulars.</p>
               <p>Then it doth ſuch good and much good:</p>
               <p n="1">(1) When it makes them more zealous for God, for his Way and Truth, and in his Worſhip; Zeal is <hi>Amor intenſus,</hi> the flame of Love, as <hi>Aquinas</hi> deſcribes it. 'Tis <hi>ignis quidam flagrantiſſimi amoris,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Uſque ad O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>vum gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am.</note> as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> long before him. Or if you
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:30413:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>will, 'tis a compound of Love and Anger, a mixt affection; it car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries forth ones love to God and his anger againſt ſin in the moſt intenſe degree. — It conſiſts in an earneſt proſecution of what is good, and in a vehement deteſtation of what is evil. O the excellency of this frame of ſpirit! You know 'tis the ſpirit of wine that commends it; the ſparkle that gives worth to the Diamond; as life gives an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency to being, ſo vivacity in operating gives an excellency to life; this is that the Lord calls for in <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.11. this he owns and crowns, <hi>Numb.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.25.11. This is moſt prevalent with God for good, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Elijah</hi>'s prayer fetcht fire from Heaven, becauſe it carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fire to Heaven. Grace turns a Sinner into a Saint; Zeal turns a Saint into a Seraphim. Much more of this you heard the other day from <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.19. Be zealous therfore.</p>
               <p>If when you come to this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance with chill, and dull, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:30413:31"/>frozen affections, and dead hearts, and there find them wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and you go thence more brisk and lively, more full of love to God, and hatred of ſin; if now you can plead the cauſe of God, and defend the Faith with more courage and reſolution; if now you can ſuffer for God more chearfully, whoſe dearly beloved Son you here ſee ſuffer'd ſo much for you, if now you can perform every holy duty with more vigour and activity; if you who were ſo remiſs and cold and ſlothful in the buſineſs of Religion, in the great concerns of God and your Souls, are now more rouzed, quickned, excited and enlarged: — When thus it works then it does you good indeed.</p>
               <p n="2">(2) When their Hearts are thaw'd and melted, ſo that they can ſorrow after a godly manner in the ſight and ſenſe of ſin: Tears are precious things; one calls 'em <hi>the Wine of Angels;</hi> another, <hi>the fat Sacrifice.</hi> Such Sacrifices were moſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:30413:31"/>acceptable, <hi>Levit.</hi> 3.3, 4, 5.</p>
               <p>The Prayers of the Saints move, their Tears compell the Lord to ſhew mercy, ſays <hi>Jerome.</hi> Were they not very precious, he would not keep a bottle for them.</p>
               <p>They never run in the right channel but when they are ſhed for ſin, then only they do us good; as St. <hi>Chryſostom</hi> well obſerves, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: For this end were they made. Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers tell us, That only reaſonable and ſinful Creatures can <hi>(gaudere &amp; maerere)</hi> rejoyce and weep. To ſpeak properly, no other upon earth can.—If now when you come to this Ordinance, your Eyes affect your Hearts, ſo that you can inwardly grieve, and outwardly weep bitterly for your ſin, as one that is in heavineſs for his only Son, or firſt-born. If when you behold a bleeding Chriſt, you have bleeding Hearts; a broken Chriſt you have broken Spirits, then does this Ordinance work for your good.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:30413:32"/>
               <p>In the time of the Law, the Paſſover was to be eaten with bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Herbs, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.8. thoſe Herbs were five, ſay the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Doctors: The Paſſover was a lively Type of Chriſt, who is our Paſſover; that Rite was inſtituted to intimate, that the Lamb of God is only ſaving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken and eaten by thoſe who are in bitterneſs of ſpirit and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of ſoul for Sin; and thus is this Holy Sacrament to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Does not a broken, bleeding Saviour call for a broken and bleeding Sinner? How can we ſee the Bread broken, and the Wine poured forth (and ſo ſhould you place your ſelves as you may ſee them) both which do repreſent and ſhew his bloody Death and bitter Paſſions, and yet have no remorſe, no contrition, no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction, no godly ſorrow in our Hearts for ſin? ſhall the Lord of Life thus ſuffer Death, and ſhed his precious innocent blood for thy, for my ſins, and ſhall not our
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:30413:32"/>Hearts be ſo affected with 'em as to weep and drop one tear for 'em?</p>
               <p>What ſad lamentation do we make for the death of our Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, eſpecially when taken away by the hand of violence, (nay they are not interred without tears who die in their beds), ſuch, ſo, ſuch was the death of our deareſt Lord</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Velloſillus</hi> diſputes the queſtion, Whether the Death of Chriſt might or ought to be lamented? He cites <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and <hi>Theophilact,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſill. <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertentias in</hi> B. Amb. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 19. <hi>pag.</hi> 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Beda</hi> and <hi>Eraſmus</hi> holding the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, from <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.28. but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes for the Affirmative, which moſt of the Fathers are for. But out of diſpute it is, That he was wounded for our iniquities, died for our ſins; and that it concerns us all to weep for our ſins which had ſo deep an hand in his Death; and Sacrament-days are proper times and ſeaſons for godly ſorrow. When your Eyes and Hearts are
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:30413:33"/>wrought and brought into this melting, mourning frame; when your ſorrows for 'em is quadrate, adequate and proportionable to that delight and complacency you have taken in them; when thus you find it at ſuch a time as this, then does this Ordinance work for your good. O that Rivers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters did this day run down our Eyes, at the remembrance of that River of blood which ran down from his ſides!—</p>
               <p n="3">(3) When it makes their Hearts to die to Sin; when they do not only diſcard, but diſguſt it, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leave but loth it; when there is not only a breaking of the Heart for Sin, but alſo a breaking of it from Sin. When their unbelief is blaſted, their pride and other luſts are mortified; when they come with ſtrong and impetuous luſts to the Lords-Table, and there get (though no more peace yet) more power over them.</p>
               <p>The death of Sin is the Souls
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:30413:33"/>life; its ruin is our riſe, its falling is our advancing; 'tis ſad to come and ſee Sin living in us, and Chriſt bleeding for us; to ſee a crucified Chriſt, and yet to find in our hearts uncrucified luſts. When you come to this ſacred and ſolemn Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and there can cry, Lord, Here is a proud unbelieving heart, an heart that does not love thee; I cannot, I will not therefore love it, it does not fear thee, but I fear it: O Lord help, help thy poor ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant with a better heart, that I may lead a better life. As it is I cannot ſerve thee, and thou wilſt not ſave me; Oh let my Sin die, but let my Soul live, and it ſhall praiſe thee for ever. Let not that which thou didſt not make, deſtroy what thine own hand hath made. O kill my pride, my paſſion. As thy Son died unto Sin for ſatisfaction, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able me to die unto Sin by Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification. Let me ſee that Chriſt died for me, even for me, by the death of Sin in me. Lord help me
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:30413:34"/>to revenge the Blood of my dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Lord upon my deareſt luſts. When thus it works, then it does you good indeed.</p>
               <p n="4">(4) When their Hearts and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are more firmly cemented and united, animoſities are remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, breaches healed, differences compoſed; when their Heart-bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings are turn'd into Heart-brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, and more Hearty-breathings after love, peace, and unity.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Austin</hi> tells us of a Street in <hi>Rome</hi> call'd <hi>Via Sacra,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Civit. Dei lib. <hi>18.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> the Holy Street; <hi>Ludovicus Vives</hi> gives the Reaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe <hi>Romulus</hi> and <hi>Tatius</hi> (King of the <hi>Sabins</hi>) made their League of Union there. Well may this be called the Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, (as on other, ſo) on this account; becauſe of that Holy League the Saints renew with God, and make one with another here.</p>
               <p>This is the great Love-Feaſt; one great end and deſign of God in this Ordinance is, by it to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and ſtrengthen Love and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:30413:34"/>amongſt his Servants; by their Communion in this Ordinance they are made to drink into one Spirit, or into oneneſs of Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</p>
               <p>But alas,<note place="margin">Nullum ſuit indoctius &amp; inſaelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſaeculum, in eo quippe nulli Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plores illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres. <hi>De Rom. Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif. lib. 4. cap. 12.</hi>
                  </note> what <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd of the Tenth Century, <hi>No Age was ſo unluckie and unlearned as that;</hi> the like may I ſay of this Seventeenth, No Age ſince our Saviours Paſſion, no, nor ſince the Worlds Creation was ever ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and diſunited as ours; we live as if we had been born upon the Mountains of <hi>Bether, (i.e.)</hi> the Mountains of Diviſion, and Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the Waters of <hi>Meribah, (i.e.)</hi> the Waters of Strife.—</p>
               <p>They who once did weep and pray together, and did ſuffer to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, cannot now ſit together at the Lords-Table; this is a Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Excellent is that paſſage of <hi>Paulinus</hi> in his Epiſtle to St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Inter Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtini Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolas. <hi>Ep. 33.</hi> in <hi>Med.</hi> Paulinus &amp; T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eraſia Auguſtino.</note> 
                  <hi>It is no marvel though we both that are abſent, be yet preſent, and being
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:30413:35"/>unacquainted, yet know one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſeeing as we have one Head, ſo we live by one Bread, walk in one Way, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When you who break Bread to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, are bound up together; when ſuch ſilver-ſhowers of Love are rained down upon your hearts as cement them more firmly, as heal your Schiſmes and repair your Breaches, and make you like the Cherubims, with your Faces look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one upon another; when you go from this Ordinance with ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger reſolutions to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace; when by it you are more inabled (as well as more engaged) to love more purely, to live more Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly, to forgive more cordially; to forget injuries, to pity and pray, and live and love as Brethren, as did thoſe Primitive Chriſtians, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.46, 47. When you that are one in ſo much, will not be two in or for a trifle; for veſtures or geſtures, or ſuch little matters. When thus
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:30413:35"/>you find it at or after a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then indeed doth it work for your good.</p>
               <p n="5">(5) When their Holineſs is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by more promoted and advanced, 'tis the end and deſign of God in all his Ordinances, eſpecially in and by this to make them who are holy more holy; them who are heavenly more heavenly. When <hi>Moſes</hi> had been with God in the Mount, he came thence with his Face ſhining:—When you go from this Ordinance with your Graces ſhining, then it does work for your good indeed.—</p>
               <p>Nothing does grace a man as Grace; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:<note place="margin">Chryſoſtom.</note> 'tis a Chriſtians great Ornament: What a pearl of price muſt holineſs be when 'tis the ſcope of Almighty God in all his Acts, Ordinances and Providences; in all his Mercies and Judgments; in our Election, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4. in our Redemption, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. in our Afflictions, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.10. Some Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances are for Converſion, ſome
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:30413:36"/>are for Confirmation, all are for our Sanctification. This Golden Oyl comes from the two Olive Trees, through the Golden pipes of his holy Inſtitutions.</p>
               <p>They ſay, that Corn never ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens more than when the Sun is in Conjunction with the Dog-ſtar; ſure am I, Holineſs never ripens more than when the Spirit of the Lord is in Conjunction with the Word and Sacraments.</p>
               <p>When you go from this ſacred Ordinance, and find you are not only more for the doing of holy things, but for the more holy do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of things, more thankful for mercies; more watchful over your hearts, words and ways, more ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual in your Converſations, more ſavory and fruitful in your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſes, more conformable in every thing to the Image of your dear Redeemer: When the power of this Ordinance runs through every vein of your Converſations; when you trade, buy and fell, when you
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:30413:36"/>pray, hear, ſanctifie his Day, and do all in the ſtrength of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; when you can ſtand at a greater diſtance from Sin and from the World; when you can look upon all the beauty of the World as blackneſs, and on all the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it as emptineſs; when you can feaſt your ſelves in God whilſt you are ſtarving in the Creature; when you can ſay in the ſincerity of your Souls, were all the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe on a flame, the fire does not touch my portion; when you can ſtand upon its ruins, and ſay tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphingly, I have loſt nothing; or as that good man, Lord,<note place="margin">Te pro om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus &amp; prae omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus the ſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris aeſtimo. <hi>Moller in Pſal. 73.25.</hi>
                  </note> thou knoweſt where all my good things are, even in thee and above with thee. <hi>Lord, whom have I in Heaven but thee, and there is none on earth that I deſire in compariſon of thee.</hi> You have there the deſire of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Soul, and the Soul of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; when thus you find it work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it does you much good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:30413:37"/>
               <p n="6">(6) When their hearts are more humbled, more deeply and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly humbled; when they meet with ſuch taſts of the Lords gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs, ſuch manifeſtations of his rich mercy, and diſcoveries of his free love, as lays them as low as the very duſt; when they can ſay as <hi>David</hi> did 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.18, 19. <hi>Who am I, O Lord God, that thou haſt brought me hitherto?</hi> What ſhall ſuch a poor pitiful piece of polluted clay, ſuch a map of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be admitted to thy Table, feaſted at thy Board, fed with the Body and Blood of the Son of God; who am I that I ſhould be embraced in his arms, that he ſhould raviſh my heart with the ſweet ſound of his precious promiſes, and rejoyce my drooping Soul with a well-groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded hope of his gracious pardons, and of the acceptance of my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and performances. I am not worthy the leaſt crumb of bread which grows upon the earth, or comes thence, much leſs of that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:30413:37"/>bread of life which came down from Heaven. The condition of my Soul had been as doleful as any mans on earth, had not free grace renewed me; as dreadful as any damned ſouls in hell, had not he in mercy to my Soul repriev'd me; O what a poor ſtarven Soul had mine been, had not the Lord of Life refreſh'd me?</p>
               <p>The moſt genuine and natural effect, which divine diſcoveries have upon a devout Soul is Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, nothing does it more kindly; and that which humbles us does not hurt us; when you can go from this Ordinance lothing and abhorring your ſelves, and ſee more of your own nothingneſs as Creatures, and vileneſs as Sinners; when you can cry with <hi>Job, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I am vile,</hi> Chap. 40.4. With the poor Publican, <hi>God be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to me a ſinner:</hi> I dare not lift mine eyes towards Heaven, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.13. When it makes and keeps us more humble, then it doth us good indeed.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:30413:38"/>
               <p n="7">(7) When their peace and joy in the Lord is increaſed, their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual comforts are enlarged, and their Souls are more aſſured of their intereſt in Chriſt, and in the everlaſting Covenant. When they can go to Chriſt and ſay, Thou art mine; to the Promiſes and ſay, all theſe are mine; when they can lay hold on the bleſſings of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and ſay, all theſe are ſealed to me in this bleſſed Sacrament. This, lo, this is the ſweet fruit the Saints find at this holy Sacrament; when their trembling Faith, is turn'd into a triumphing Faith; their Faith of adherence into a Faith of evidence and aſſurance. There is a threefold fulneſs of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, a full allurance of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.2. of Hope, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.11. and of Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. O what a ſweet and precious, what a rich and rare Jewel is this! Grace purifies; Aſſurance pacifies; Grace brings the Soul to Heaven; Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance brings Heaven into the Soul:
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:30413:38"/>Grace is better than Peace, but Peace is ſweeter than Grace; Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is a flower of Paradiſe, a ſparkle of Glory, Heaven on this ſide Heaven, an Anchor at Sea, a Shield at Land, a Staff to ſupport, a Sword to defend, Bread to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, Wine to chear, and Balm to cure the Soul of man.—</p>
               <p>When at and by this precious Ordinance your Souls are fill'd with joy unſpeakable, and full of glory; when thoſe black clouds of fears and jealouſies are diſperſed, and thoſe bitter ſtorms of Soul-trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles are blown over; when brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beams, and clearer calms, and ſweeter comforts flow in upon your Souls; when thus you find it, then has the Sacrament been working for your good.</p>
               <p>'Tis one great end of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to ſeal his peoples Graces; many a child of God can tell you, that by this Ordinance they have arriv'd at a great meaſure of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, they have come empty and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:30413:39"/>gone hence full; they have come with fears and doubts upon them, and have gone away with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of joy and peace; the Lord has met them at his Table, has ſpoken peace unto their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, has clear'd up their Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for Heaven, and now they can ſpeak of the great things he has done in it, and by it too, for their precious Souls.</p>
               <p>This Ordinance was inſtituted for his peoples growth in Grace, and for their ſenſe of Grace; for the augmentation of it, and for the manifeſtation of it.</p>
               <p>By it Grace grows up to its full ſtature, and juſt proportion; 'Tis for ſealing too; the Sacrament is a good friend to the Spirit, (be it ſpoken with reverence) and the Spirit is a greater friend to the Sacrament, and both are great friends to the Soul, ſealing it up unto the day of redemption, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.30. As a Seal doth confirm and ſettle the mind of the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:30413:39"/>Buyer, ſo doth the Sacrament ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and aſſure the heart of a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever; O how willing is the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty the Soul be out of doubt of its Sanctification here and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation hereafter.—To which God of his infinite mercy, for the merits of his Son, by the conduct of his holy Spirit, at laſt bring us. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>The End of the Firſt Sermon.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:30413:40"/>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:30413:40"/>
               <head>The Second SERMON</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>On Micah 2.7.</hi>
                     </bibl> Is the Spirit of the Lord ſtraitned?<note place="margin">
                        <hi>July</hi> the 20th. 1673</note> Do not my words do good to him that walketh upright, or upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly?</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Word ſpoken upon his Wheels is like Apples of Gold in pictures of Silver. I may ſay of this, 'Tis <hi>verbum ſuper rotas,</hi> a word in ſeaſon; then will the Sermon be moſt profitable, when the ſubject is moſt ſeaſonable. The Text is like a well-drawn <hi>picture,</hi> it hath an <hi>eye</hi> on every man; as you will ſee anon. I ſhall draw aſide
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:30413:41"/>the curtain, that ſo you may view it, and it may view you.—I will waſte no time in the beginning, that I may want no time in the end. I am ſhewing when this Ordinance of the Supper doth work for the Saints benefit and advantage. I have hinted ſeven, and ſhall now proceed methodically unto the eighth in order; of which ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinctly: For enough is better than all.</p>
               <p n="8">(8) Then doth this Ordinance work for your good, when your Souls are more corroborated and ſtrengthned, and your power is more encreaſed: Obſerve it, pray.</p>
               <p>The Miniſtry of the Word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets ſpiritual life; The Sacrament preſerves and increaſeth ſpiritual life.</p>
               <p>The Word lays the Baſis or Foundation of Grace; the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment carries on the Building.</p>
               <p>The Word is inſtituted to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant Grace, to work the truth of Grace, where it is not: The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:30413:41"/>is to promote the growth of it, where it is. The Miniſtry of the Word is a converting Ordinance; the Sacrament is a confirming Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance: That's the breeding, and this the feeding Ordinance. If now you come to the Lords. Table very weak, your Graces very feeble, your Faith and Love, and other Graces very little. If it may be ſaid of you as it was of the Church of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> Rev. 3.8. <hi>Thou hast but (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,) a little ſtrength;</hi> and then you go away ſtronger, your Faith more encreaſed, your hope more quickened, your obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ential and penitential reſolutions more ſtrengthned, your corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons more eaſily ſubdued, tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions more eaſily repulſed, your aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions more raiſed and enlarged, your hearts more eſtabliſhed, duties more ſpiritually performed, the world more eaſily conquered and van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed. If now you find your ſelves more able to do, to ſuffer for God, or from God; if now
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:30413:42"/>you are more fitted for active and paſſive obedience, if you can go thorow all Chriſtian duties with more alacrity and cheerfulneſs, if you can apply the promiſes, and live by Faith upon the Fatherly providence and faithful promiſes of God. When thus you find it, then hath this Ordinance been doing you good.</p>
               <p n="9">(9) When at and by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment your love to Jeſus Chriſt is more enflamed; when this little drop ſwells into an Ocean, and this ſpark becomes a flame; when it may be ſaid of your love to God, to Chriſt, to his way, day, people, Ordinances, as is ſaid of the Waters of the Sanctuary, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47.3, 4, 5. that 'tis ſtill higher and higher, from the ankles to the knees, thence to the loins, and then unpaſſable; ſo in the preſent caſe.</p>
               <p>Is it poſſible we ſhould be ſuch conſtant Gueſts at the Lords-Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and daily ſee before our eyes a crucified Chriſt, and yet go
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:30413:42"/>thence with ſo little love to him, and longings after him? Can we fee ſo much love in his heart to us, and ſhall we be contented with ſo little love in our hearts to him? —<hi>Per vulnera videmus viſcera.</hi> 'Tis an heart of Adamant that will neither <hi>impendere,</hi> nor <hi>repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere;</hi> which will neither begin in love nor love him then who has thus begun, Behold what manner of love the Father hath beſtowed on us, in beſtowing his Son upon us; We call not upon people to behold things common and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary; <hi>Paul</hi> calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>great love,</hi> Eph. 2.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>a love paſſing knowledg;</hi> Heart-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming words indeed; See <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.19. He laid down his precious life and deareſt blood for us, he died <hi>Noſtro loco,</hi> in our place and ſtead; <hi>Nostro commodo,</hi> for our benefit and good; for our ſin as the meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious cauſe, and for our good as the final cauſe, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.26. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. Greater love than this can
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:30413:43"/>no man ſhew. Did ever Mother love her own Child ſo as to waſh it in her own blood? thus lov'd he us, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. <hi>God ſo loved the world,</hi>—ſo; How's that? ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully, ſo infinitely; ſo—but I cannot tell you how, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt leave it ſo; admiring and not once attempting to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it, but the Son of God can, <hi>Even as the Father loved me, ſo have I loved you.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 15.9.</note> Here was the higheſt, pureſt, freeſt, ſweeteſt and choiceſt love that ever was in the world.</p>
               <p>We conclude they love us who will ſpeak kindly and courteouſly to us, or a word in ſeaſon for us; much more if they will hazzard their lives and fortunes by eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our cauſe and quarrel; did not our dear Redeemer all this and more? Lord, (now ſays the poor Chriſtian) thou haſt laid down thy life, and thereby haſt manifeſted thy love to me; Now will I part with my deareſt luſts, I
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:30413:43"/>will be their death, and ſo ſhew my love to thee; ſhall a damning luſt live, and a ſaving Chriſt die? Shall the man die that kills my Son or Father, and ſhall my Sin live which ſlays my Saviour? Well, if I can do no more, I will do no leſs than love thee my deareſt Lord with all my heart and might, and ſtrength. The more vile thou waſt made for me, the dearer to my dying day ſhalt thou be unto me. When thus it works, then it does you good indeed.</p>
               <p n="10">(10) When your hearts which were before at a diſtance from him are by it drawn nearer to him; and your deſires are more drawn out after him.</p>
               <p>There is a twofold diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and Man.</p>
               <p>The one is natural; as he is the Creator, Man a creature; He infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, Man finite; this is an infinite diſtance.</p>
               <p>The other is Moral, as he is Holy, and Man impure; this is a greater
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:30413:44"/>diſtance than the former, if we may ſuppoſe an <hi>infinito infinitius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By nature we are all afar off from God<note place="margin">n="*" Non inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallo loco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſed pravitate morum.</note>, by Grace through Chriſt we are made nigh, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.13. yet nigher we may be by much than yet we are; and 'tis our great buſineſs in every Ordinance to get nearer to him, if you ſcan that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous place, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. <hi>Let us draw near with a true heart.</hi> If now we find our confidence drawn more out after him; and that we can reſt more upon him, and truſt more in him; if for what our Souls want we can with an humble boldneſs go to him, and ſay, Lord, Here is my treaſure, my fullneſs, my All; I am dead, but to thee I come for life and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning grace; I have a proud heart, but unto thee do I addreſs my ſelf; I know thou who giveſt more (and better) grace to the humble; canſt give me grace to be more humble. I am impotent, but to thee I come for ſtrength againſt my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:30413:44"/>and for holy duties; Lord, I am nothing, I have nothing, I can do nothing, I am good for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; I cannot plead my merits but thy mercy; unworthy I am to live, unfit I am to die. When thus we find it with us at or after a Sacrament, then has it been work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for our good.</p>
               <p n="11">(11) When you have the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace ſealed, and the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters thereof impreſſed upon your hearts; when Sacrament-days are healing and ſealing days; the Saints are ſealed with the holy Spirit of Promiſe; ſuch ſacred ſtamps he ſets upon their Souls as ſhall never be obliterated. Many a child of God has here had <hi>monumentum aere pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennius;</hi> when by this Ordinance you gain ſuch full evidences of his love, ſuch influences of his Grace, ſuch experiences of his Truth, ſuch aſſiſtances from his Spirit, ſuch ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications and confirmations of the Goſpel-promiſes, as you never had before. When thus you find it with
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:30413:45"/>you, you may ſafely and ſolidly conclude, it has been working for your good.</p>
               <p n="12">(12) Once more, and in a word. —When more glorious conqueſts over your ſpiritual enemies are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, when prevailing luſts are vanquiſhed, and fiery temptations are quenched, (and all theſe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders one drop of his precious blood (when taken down by Faith) can do) when you can go from this Ordinance triumphing over and trampling upon the neck of your unbelief, and pride, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this ſome have done; when you can come from the Sacrament as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did out of the Red Sea, and ſee your ſpiritual enemies bleeding, gaſping, dying, dead; your luſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, but your Souls preſerved. When thus you feel and find it, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Sacrament has done you good and much good.</p>
               <p>Q. 5. <hi>How doth it appear that the Spirit of the Lord is not ſo ſtraitned, but that he can cauſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:30413:45"/>this Ordinance to work for your good?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 'Tis a truth written with a Sun-beam; 'tis <hi>tanquam ex tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pode dictum;</hi> None of thoſe Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles may vye with this, The Spirit of the Lord hath owned and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it to others, and therefore can to you.</p>
               <p>The Spirit of the Lord is God, and what cannot a Great, Almighty God do? What will not a good and gracious God do by his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances for his people? His arm is not ſhortned, nor love leſſened or impaired.</p>
               <p>Of all the Fathers (were I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to one alone) I ſhould fix on <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide S. Ambroſii de ſp. ſ. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1, 3, 6, 7, 9, 11, 14, 20. <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4, 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12. <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 5, 12, 14, 17, 23, <hi>Tom.</hi> 4.</note> for he hath writ e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to evince the Deity and divine operations of the Holy Ghoſt; from him I might extract what would abundantly confirm the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition under our preſent <hi>conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;</hi> but I <hi>forbear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As St. <hi>Paul</hi> reaſoned concerning
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:30413:46"/>the Reſurrection of the dead, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Apology for himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> Act. 20.8. <hi>Why ſhould it be thought a thing unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable with you that God ſhould raiſe the dead?</hi> So may I ſay to you in this Apology for the power of the Spirit, Why ſhould it be thought a thing unreaſonable for the Spirit of the Lord to do all theſe things in, at, and by this ſacred and ſolemn Ordinance?</p>
               <p>The Doctrine under debate nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exceeds the bounds of Faith, nor is it contrary to the experience of the Saints. Doubtleſs ſome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe walls have had ſweet expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the powerful influences and mighty workings of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord in their Hearts, and upon their Spirits at this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.—But we will review and ſuccinctly reflect upon ſome of the forementioned particulars; we ſhall fix on four or five, the reſt you may clear up to your ſelves in your private Meditations.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:30413:46"/>
               <p>I remember that <hi>Athenagoras</hi> an <hi>Athenian</hi> (but a Chriſtian) Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher diſputing for the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Dead, hath a paſſage which is pertinent to what I have in hand. The impotency of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ariſeth either from his igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, ſomething he would do, but knows not what nor how; or from his inſufficiency or weakneſs, though he knows what and how to effect, yet a power is wanting to accompliſh and bring it to paſs; neither of which (ſays he truly) can be affirmed of God, who is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely wiſe and powerful. The ſame ſay I of the Spirit of the Lord; He is a Spirit of Wiſdom and Power, and both infinite, they are really the ſame with his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He knows how to break the Heart for Sin, and he can as eaſily bring it into a melting mourning frame; alas, we may pray and hear, and wait in the uſe of means, and yet our Hearts remain as hard as
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:30413:47"/>Adamant;<note place="margin">Fortiter <hi>yet</hi> Suaviter.</note> but when the Spirit of the Lord once takes them in hand, he works irreſiſtibly and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, <hi>a nullo duro corde reſpuitur;</hi> when he breaks in and breaths upon the Soul, then it begins to thaw and melt, and mourn.</p>
               <p>We read of <hi>Peters</hi> ſins, excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great and very many were they, ſadly circumſtantiated, highly aggravated.<note place="margin">Mat. 26.75</note> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> even now (and but juſt now) had a forewarning from Chriſt; <hi>Peter</hi> was dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd of Chriſt, none of the Twelve more, <hi>John</hi> ever excepted: He was the firſt whom Chriſt call'd to be an Apoſtle; <hi>Peter</hi> was often ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted when others were exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. He yielded eaſily to the Temptation, and that of a poor ſilly Damſel: He ſinned not in a corner; once and again, and a third time denies Chriſt with curſing and ſwearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet when our Bleſſed Saviour began to look, and the Spirit of the Lord ſet in to work, then <hi>Peter</hi> went out and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:30413:47"/>wept bitterly, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. <hi>ult.</hi> A ſtrange look and a ſtrong look it was that thus quickly broke his heart in pieces; he lookt (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Theophylact</hi> obſerves) with a look of love, with a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nign aſpect. Chriſt looks, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit works, the Conſcience ſtirs, and out he goes and weeps ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He knows how to break the Heart from Sin; and can eaſily do it, be it a darling luſt, a Delilah, never ſo near or dear, <hi>a peccatum in deliciis.</hi> He can make a full, a final, a total and an eternal Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce between you and them, though your luſts were mighty Hoſts, he can lay them dead at your feet. I appeal from Gods Book to your own Breaſts for the proof hereof.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He can increaſe your Graces: are they weak? he can ſtrengthen them; if little he can increaſe them. There is no Corruption ſo ſtrong but he can make it weak;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:30413:48"/>no Grace ſo weak, but he can make it ſtrong. This Men cannot, Means cannot, Angels cannot, but He can.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He can make you Holy as he is Holy; that is, for Quality, not for Equality; Holy in way of reſemblance; Holy in all manner of Converſation; all that Holineſs in Saints or Angels is of his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He can fill your Hearts with aſſurance of his Grace in you, and of Gods Grace and Favour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you. The influences of the Spirit work Grace, and the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of the Spirit diſcover Grace: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Now we have received not the ſpirit of the world, but the Spirit which is of God, that we might know the things that are freely given to us of God. He bears witneſs with our ſpirits that we are the Sons of God. Et quando Spiritus testatur, quaenam relinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ambiguitas?</hi> The Spirit brings the Heart to the command, that's
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:30413:48"/>holineſs; he brings the promiſe to the heart, that's aſſurance. In a word,<note place="margin">Sp. S. irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectum, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinat vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem, ſigillat Animum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> he can turn your Water into Wine, your night into day; he can remove your fears, reſolve your doubts, revive your Souls, recruit your Comforts. Others on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walk in the light of Gods Providence, he can make you to walk in the light of his Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
               <p n="6">6. He alſo who reconciled Man to God can reconcile Man to Man. He can cement your hearts. The ſtones of the Temple were ſo cloſely cemented, as if they all had been but one; He can unite you thus too. When the Sons of <hi>Brutus</hi> and the <hi>Vitellii</hi> conſpired with <hi>Tarquinius</hi> his Embaſſadours againſt the Conſul, they drank the blood of a man to confirm their Amity and Unity; You are now a going to drink the precious Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, what hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders but the Spirit of the Lord may ſhed abroad his love in your hearts,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:30413:49"/>and make you live in love? what are all the motions of the Spirit but tenders of Love? or what is the zeal of the Spirit, but the print of love? or the Graces of the Spirit but engagements to love? He can give you ſuch hearts, as will be,</p>
               <p>Afraid of every little Sin:</p>
               <p>Amended with every little Croſs:</p>
               <p>Affected with every little mercy.</p>
               <p>The Spirit of the Lord hath power enough to give a being to us, and hath he not power e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to do any thing in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us? Can he give a being to his Ordinances, and cannot he give a bleſſing to them? He can do every thing, and therefore This— But that ſhall ſerve for the fifth <hi>Query.</hi> —The improvement of. the point is not the leaſt conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able part of my work, and indeed 'tis all that now remains. Here is a word of Counſel, and a word of Comfort; ſomething which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns Sinners, and ſomething too
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:30413:49"/>which concerns the Saints. I would not diſcourage the weak, yet muſt I awaken the ſecure.</p>
               <p>I begin with the Counſels, ſuch firſt as concern you that are Saints; and I have ſomething to ſay in General, ſomething in particular.</p>
               <p>Two things would I ſay in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,—<hi>Is not the Spirit of the Lord ſo ſtraitned, but that he can cauſe this Ordinance to do you good?</hi> Then ſee that,</p>
               <p n="1">1. You believe this Truth, and believe it firmly and undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The Spirit is God, as Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as the Father, or as the Son. To an Almighty power nothing is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, nay nothing difficult. When God promiſed <hi>Abraham</hi> a Son in his old age, what a hard task was here for God? <hi>Sarah</hi> could not believe it, <hi>ſhe laughed;</hi> but what ſaith the Lord, <hi>Is any thing too hard for me?</hi> He can do it becauſe he is omnipotent, and he will do it becauſe he hath promiſed to do it; 'tis a truth as
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:30413:50"/>full of comfort to the Saints, as is the Sea of water, or the Sun of light; therefore believe it ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And ſee that you</p>
               <p n="2">2. Look for good; for great workings in and by this Ordinance from the Spirit of the Lord. And look well to this Ordinance that it do you good; for if it do you no good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it will do you hurt; if it be not bread, it will be poyſon; it will ſet you either a ſtep nearer to Heaven, or nearer to Hell. Who can ſay when he hath been at a Sermon, or at a Sacrament (as ſome Tradeſmen may when their accompts are caſt up) I have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther got, nor loſt. Be you well aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that if it do not ſtrengthen your graces, it will ſtrengthen your corruptions. This is a ſad ſaying, but not more ſad than true; others have found it ſo, and ſo may you; it will further you either in the way to glory, or in the way to miſery. O that whilſt the ſound of theſe words is in your ears, the ſavour
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:30413:50"/>of them were upon your hearts.</p>
               <p>But to come yet more cloſe to the buſineſs; in order hereunto perhaps ſome of you may enquire. And it brings me to the Sixth Query.</p>
               <p>Q. 6. <hi>What courſe muſt a ſerious Chriſtian take or hold, that the Spirit of the Lord may cauſe this bleſſed Ordinance to work for his good?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this numerous Auditory I am in hopes there are not many, if any, but they ſeriouſly deſire the Ordinances may do their Souls good. They would not pray, nor hear, nor receive in vain. Well, I will confine my diſcourſe to this Ordinance before you, take theſe ten Directions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Carefully prepare your hearts for it if you would profit by it. Till the Earth be prepared you caſt not in the ſeed; till the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:30413:51"/>be tuned, you do not begin to play. Till your Hearts be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared you cannot receive worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; Gods Diſpenſations are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſuited to our Diſpoſitions. Thoſe Beaſts which came in to <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark unclean, went out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain unclean.— You know the <hi>Jews</hi> had their preparation for the Paſſover, <hi>Job.</hi> 19.14. And is not this an Ordinance every way as holy and venerable? When our Bleſſed Saviour was about to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute this Ordinance, it was his pleaſure the Houſe ſhould firſt be fitted and prepared in which he was to do it, <hi>Mark</hi> 14.15. Is there not as much, nay much more need our hearts be fitted and prepared? Well then ſay I to you as <hi>Samuel</hi> did to the Elders of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.5. <hi>Sanctifie your ſelves and come with me unto the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice;</hi> put your hearts in order.</p>
               <p>Theſe two things have a ſpecial eye unto:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>(1) To get an Underſtanding.</item>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:30413:51"/>
                  <item>(2) An humble Heart.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">(1) Get an Underſtanding Heart; when the Lord appear'd to <hi>Solomon</hi> in <hi>Gibeon,</hi> and ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, <hi>Ask what I ſhall give thee?</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Give unto thy Servant an underſtanding Heart,</hi> ſays <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> in <hi>verſ.</hi> the 9th. Some ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the words,<note place="margin">Cor dicile; Sapientiam circa agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da; Cor capax di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinarum legum.</note> 
                  <hi>Cor audiens,</hi> an hearing Heart; others, <hi>Cor intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens aut ſapiens,</hi> an underſtanding, wiſe heart. He asked Wiſdom; with a great deal of Wiſdom; had not he been wiſe before, he had not known the worth of wiſdom. When you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are about theſe Sacramental duties, pray for an Underſtanding heart. Amongſt the Graces requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to qualifie a Communicant, Knowledg is neither the laſt nor the leaſt conſiderable. Knowledg of what? may ſome ſay.</p>
               <p>I anſwer (I) the Knowledge of our ſelves,<note place="margin">Eſt Diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinarum omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherrima &amp; maxima ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum noſſe. <hi>Cle. Alex. Paeda. l. 3.</hi> in initio.</note> of our miſery and of our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady, of our want of Chriſt, and of the worth of Chriſt, of our intereſt in Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the Covenant, and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:30413:52"/>conſequently of our right to this Ordinance, which is one ſeal of that Covenant.</p>
               <p n="2">(2) The Knowledg of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, what it is and whoſe it is, and for what ends it is; a Phyſical potion may do the Patient good, though he know not the ingredients of which it is compounded, nor the Apothecary by whom it is prepared, nor yet the Doctor by whom it is preſcribed; becauſe it works phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, naturally; but in this caſe it is not ſo, becauſe the Sacrament works morally. In ſhort, if you be found guilty of much ignorance, I fear me you will find little good by this Ordinance; for it works not <hi>ex opere operato</hi> but <hi>ex opere operantis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, above all, let it be your care to bring with you an humble Heart. At the Marriage of <hi>Peleus</hi> and <hi>Thetis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lud. Vives <hi>on</hi> Aug. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> a Golden Ball was ſent in amongſt the Feaſters, having this Inſcription on it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Let the faireſt have it.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:30413:52"/>
               <p>Here are choiceſt comforts, ſweet, ſanctifying, ſatisfying comforts to be had at the Lords Table, ſuch as will rejoyce and tranſport the Soul infinitely, on them the Motto is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, let the humbleſt have 'em; of all the Graces which Chriſt commands our imitation of him in, humility is one of the firſt and choiceſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly.</hi> q.d. Your care ſhould be to be holy as I am holy, and merciful as I am merciful: But above all, be ſure to learn from me to be humble.</p>
               <p>In the Lords eye no heart like the humble heart, 'tis the grand Sacrifice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.2. A proud man will preſume to come to the Table of the Lord, no man ſooner, but the Lord will not come nigh to him at his Table; No, he beholds him afar off.</p>
               <p>How can he expect a gift in love from Gods hand, who muſt not have a look in love from Gods eye?</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:30413:53"/>
               <p>A proud heart is not fit for this Ordinance, nor was ever this Ordinance intended for a proud heart. But the poor humble, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Soul the Spirit of the Lord will enrich and fill with good things. What <hi>Tully</hi> ſaid of Pronuntiation in an Orator, that ſays St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> is humility in a Chriſtian; 'tis the firſt, ſecond and third Grace.</p>
               <p>The humble heart is a ſpiritual <hi>vacuum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cor Humile eſt vacuum ſpirituale. <hi>Guliel. Pariſ.</hi> Sicut natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra non.—</note> as the God of Nature will not permit a natural; ſo the God of all Grace cannot permit a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual; filled it ſhall be with Grace here and Glory hereafter. I have often thought of that paſſage of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his Enarrations on the 93. <hi>Pfalm,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Magis Deo placet hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militas in malis fact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is, quàm ſuperbia in Bonis.</note> The great God is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pleas'd with humility in a bad, than with pride in a good action.</p>
               <p>He that comes to this or that, or any holy Ordinance, without Faith and Humility, whatever good is diſpenſed, he goes without. For he hath nothing to take a mercy with, wanting the hand of Faith;
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:30413:53"/>and nothing to put a mercy in; not having an humble heart. The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit reſted on the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> not for her Virginity,<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> but for her hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Would you have the Spirit of the Lord to do you good at and by this Ordinance, then be ſerious in ſelf-examination. 'Tis a neceſſary duty; on this the ſtreſs is laid; let a man examine himſelf and ſo let him come and take and eat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is a trying time, and this is the trying Ordinance; it trys how your pulſe beats; how you can pronounce Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; what propenſions you have towards the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Faith; As in the <hi>Marian</hi> times, how mens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations ſtood towards the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,—well—as you are tryed by it, ſo muſt you try your ſelves for it; the knowledg of your ſelves is neceſſary as you heard even now. Now the moſt expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous way to know our ſelves is to try our ſelves: Search,</p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:30413:54"/>
               <list>
                  <item>(1) Then till you have found out the evil that is in you; the pride, Hypocriſie, ſelf-love, unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and mortifie them; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what error is in the head, what blood is in the hand, what luſts are in the heart; what it is that hinders your growth in Grace, that interrupts your peace, that interpoſeth between you and the light of Gods Countenance. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing there is at the bottom, ſome <hi>Jonah</hi> that diſturbs the Ship, ſome <hi>Achan</hi> that troubles the Camp; you would have more joy and peace: Know, the Spirit firſt ſets the Soul a ſearching, and then he comes a ſealing; God may hide his face in point of Soveraignty, but he does it commonly in caſe of ſin, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.40. <hi>Let us ſearch, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>(2) Search till you have found out the good that's in you; for you muſt acknowledg the Graces that you have, before you can receive the comforts which you want.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:30413:54"/>
               <p>Thirdly, Be careful to excite and to blow up thoſe graces which the Spirit of the Lord hath implanted in you. 'Tis not enough that you have grace, no, no, a man that hath grace may receive unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (not acting his graces) though he cannot be an unworthy recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Now's a proper ſeaſon for the exerting and exerciſing of your Graces: What Graces may ſome enquire?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, chiefly four, Faith and Love, Humility and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; all noble Graces; they are <hi>Theologiae Quadriga.</hi> Faith gets all; Love ſpends all; Humility keeps all; the grace of Faith lays up for Chriſt; the grace of Love lays out for Chriſt; and the grace of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity keeps all for Chriſt. Of this laſt grace I have ſpoken in the firſt Direction; of the other three a word or two now.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Act Faith now; the acting of Faith is the way to increaſe your Faith, and to obtain peace
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:30413:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>and aſſurance; all the Devils in Hell cannot do you that hurt at this Ordinance as your own unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving hearts can and will. I dare and do aſſure you, That if the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit do not weaken your unbelief, your unbelief will ſtraiten the Spirit, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Fides non eſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuro ad Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtiam:</note> 
                  <hi>Cajetan</hi> at a Conference with <hi>Luther,</hi> poſitively aſſerted, That Faith is not neceſſary for an Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Communicant. Could I but <hi>pro tempore</hi> abjure Senſe and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſo much unman my ſelf as to admit that ſcandalous Doctrine, and deviliſh figment of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, I would concur with him in that ignorant and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent aſſertion; but no ſuch traſh will paſs here; you have not ſo learned Chriſt. Well then, act Faith, and this will ſanctifie you for this Ordinance, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.9. and it will ſanctifie this Ordinance to you, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15. God the Father conveys all good to us through Chriſt, and Chriſt conveys all good to us
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:30413:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>through Faith. <hi>Dormit Fides &amp; dormit Chriſtus.</hi> Chriſt is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, the Sacrament is the Conduit, Faith is the Cock, the heart is the Veſſel. Turn but this Cock, and the oyl of joy and peace will flow in abundantly into your Souls from the fountain of living waters.</p>
               <p>There are two ſpecial ſeaſons for a Chriſtian to act faith in; the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer when under ſore afflictions; then he muſt live by Faith. Faith is an inquiſitive grace, it will not be quiet till it have found out the Sin that hath provokt God, and procur'd the rod; Faith then eyes the Sin to humble the Soul, and the promiſe to comfort the Soul. Faith eyes the hand inflicting, and works patience; and it eyes the ſin procuring, and works repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. When God is ſtriking for ſin, Faith will be ſtriking at ſin; Faith will make great afflictions little, bitter potions ſweet; unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief makes ſhort afflictions long, and eaſie burdens heavy. Faith will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:30413:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Soul to pray; Prayer i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the very breath of Faith. Faith is all for Prayer, and Prayer is all for Faith; the latter, when about di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitutions and holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances: what Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.5. that faith Faith to us, <hi>Without me ye can do nothing.</hi> Nothing acceptable to God, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing profitable to your ſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Act Love and Charity; now's the time to have your Hearts fired, inflamed with love to God, and filled with love to Man. As the Sacrament receiv'd without Faith is receiv'd without fruit; ſo, if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd without love, 'tis receiv'd without life.</p>
               <p>Love puts life into a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicant, and Love puts life into a Sacrament. When the Lord Jeſus was a dying on the Croſs, he ſtretcht out his Arms to both Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors; to teach us (ſurely) when we come unto this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to be in charity with all men. All men love their Friends,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:30413:56"/>but Communicants ſhould love their enemies;<note place="margin">Amare eſt bonum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cui velle, non noſtrâ ſed ejus cauſâ. <hi>Aqu<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Amicos in te, inimicos propter te. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>elſe what do they more than others,</hi> Mat. 5.47.</p>
               <p>The Spirit of the Lord is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Love, and loves to do good to ſuch as live in love.</p>
               <p>But we cannot live in love may ſome ſay.</p>
               <p>No? It may ſo happen you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live in peace; <hi>I am for peace,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>but when I ſpeak, they are for war.</hi> Well, but you may live in love; you may love them though they hate you: If ſo you do, your duty is done, and you may come in hope and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to receive good by this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; carry theſe two things along with you.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. 'Tis connatural to a Sinner to hate a Saint; if he chance to love him, 'tis becauſe he is of a ſweet nature, or for ſome external Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations; not becauſe he is of a ſanctify'd nature; Holineſs is the thing he diſguſts and hates.</item>
                  <item>2. If any man love not the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:30413:57"/>Lord Jeſus, think it not ſtrange if he hate you; never court his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, for his love is not worth the having, who thinks not Chriſt worth loving.</item>
               </list>
               <p>See <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s Book to <hi>Scapula,</hi> who was a great enemy to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the beginning of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Renew your Repentance, and the Spirit of the Lord will do you good by this Ordinance. The <hi>Jews</hi> before the Paſſover cleanſed all their Veſſels which they ſuſpected might have any leaven in them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they burned all they could find, and what they could not find, they curſed. Thus ſhould we do by our ſins, we ſhould ſearch every cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of our hearts, and every paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of our lives, (if poſſible); We ſhould go with a <hi>Melius inquiren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum;</hi> What have I done ſince the laſt time I was at the Lords-Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? What ſin have I lapſt into, what diſhonour have I done to God, what diſſervice to Religion? and now repent of all. Do as the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:30413:57"/>Royal Prophet did,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Calculavi. Conſultavi.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.59. <hi>I conſidered my ways, and turn'd my feet into thy Teſtimonies. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered; i.e.</hi> I ſet my head and heart and mind on work; I turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them over and over; upſide down; I weighed them in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance: I thought on them; <hi>i.e.</hi> what they were, whither they did tend, in what they would end; I ſaw they were not good, holy, right; I durſt not own them at the great day; and I turned, I ſaw 'twas high time to turn. I buſied not my ſelf about other mens ways and works, my own found me work enough.</p>
               <p>A ſerious Conſideration of our ways helps us to a ſight of the evil of them; a ſight of the evil of our ways, helps us to godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for them,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.10.</note> and godly ſorrow worketh repentance. The Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill is never ſo lothſom and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive as when you ſtir in it; you never ſo fully diſcern the Bran as when you ſift the Corn; you will
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:30413:58"/>never diſcern ſin, mourn for ſin, or turn from ſin till you conſider your ways. O pray remember, only the true penitent is the right quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd Communicant. Say, Lord, here is the ſin, (by ſearch I have found it out) that hath ſo highly diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured thee, ſo greatly troubled me, 'tis this that ſoiled my Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences; cankered my Aſſurance; I loth my ſelf now and repent in duſt and aſhes.</p>
               <p>Appoſite to what I have in hand is that paſſage of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ita &amp; nos quando ad altare Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municaturi accedimus, venemum peſſimum: <hi>viz.</hi> Iracundia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, invidiam, ſuberbiam, avaritiam, haec ſunt animarum venena, iſta prius repellamus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Feria</hi> 2. <hi>poſt Dom.</hi> 1. <hi>Quadrag.</hi> the ſubject or argument of his Sermon is, The univerſal or general day of Judgment, <hi>Serpens cum venerit ad bibendum, aquam priuſquam bibit, extra fontem evomit venenum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um?</hi> Even as a Serpent coming to drink; firſt it vomits up its poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and then drinketh; ſo when we come to the Lords Table, we muſt firſt (by humble confeſſion, which is <hi>vomitus ſordium animae</hi>) caſt up and vomit out our poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:30413:58"/>the worſt of poyſos; <hi>viz.</hi> Anger and Hatred, Envy, Pride, and Covetouſneſs, Sacriledg, Theft and Luxury; theſe are the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the bane of the Soul; away with theſe, and then we ſhall be ſatisfied with thoſe Spiritual dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Heavenly viands, <hi>viz.</hi> the body<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and blood of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Athenagoras</hi> the <hi>Athenian</hi> Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher hath a parallel paſſage in the very beginning of his Book <hi>de Reſur. Mortuorum. Nec Medicus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundere ſalutare pharmacum aegroto corpori apte poteſt, niſi vitioſa prius expurgârit, aut affluentem purulenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiam cohibuerit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Conſtantly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly wait, diligently and duly attend upon the Lord in every Ordinance, if you would have the Spirit of the Lord to do you good in and by This; let this be your practice and it ſhall be your praiſe; if it be ſomewhat painful, yet you ſhall find it very gainful; it is your
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:30413:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>duty, and your glory too. The Merchants Ship takes not in all its Lading at one Port; nor does the Chriſtian enrich himſelf with trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of grace and peace at one Ordinance only. He hath inſtituted none to be kickt at or neglected; ſlight him in that, and he may you in This.<note place="margin">Vide ſis <hi>Aug.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>29. Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymo,</hi> de illo loco <hi>Jacobi.</hi>
                  </note> His Ordinances are Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels of Grace, and Channels of Comfort; if you neglect him in one, he may ſuſpend his influences at an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. As every command of God muſt be obeyed and obſerved; a wilful violation of one amounts to a total neglect, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.10. ſo eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ordinance of God muſt be uſed and improved; a partial obſervance is an argument of inſincerity; 'tis a vain deceit to excuſe defects of one duty, neglects of one Ordinance, by care of another.</p>
               <p>As all the commands, ſo all the Ordinances of the Lord are equal in regard of him;<note place="margin">Pſa. 119.6.</note> all being rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the ſame authority, which you contemn when your own will
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:30413:59"/>is, made the meaſure of your obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. I urge this Rule the rather, becauſe ſome of you I ſee for the prayers of the Church more vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but for the Sacrament more remiſs and indifferent; others, all for this, not at all for that. But if you would find acceptance, if you would profit by any Ordinance, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove all; thus doing, doubtleſs the good Spirit of the Lord will do you good.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what are thoſe other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, may ſome ſay?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Meditation and Prayer, and the Miniſtry of the Word. <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio est mentis ditatio;</hi> 'tis the enriching of the mind. The Royal Prophet was real for it and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in it; who ever more? O how ſweet was his Meditation of God, his laws and ways to him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.34.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> was us'd to ſay, Three things make a good Divine, Prayer,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:30413:60"/>Meditation and Temptation; the firſt makes him holy; the ſecond makes him rich and full, the third makes him an experienced Divine. And will not that which makes a good Preacher make a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian? Surely it will.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Prayer; he makes his people fruitful and joyful; but where? why in his houſe of Prayer; Prayer is a mighty friend to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Sacrament is a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty friend to Prayer; and both are great friends to a gracious Soul?</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Miniſtry of the Word; as the Word is a Word of Grace, ſo 'tis a Word of Peace; by this the Spirit of the Lord begins the work, and by it he carries on the work.</p>
               <p>Two things take along with you.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. He will be waited on in a right manner, and in a due order in all his Ordinances, or he takes himſelf as not waited on at all; though the Inſtitutions or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:30413:60"/>be different, yet the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and authority and ultimate end in all is the ſame.</item>
                  <item>2. He will be waited on conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually; as we cannot ſet the Sun a time when it ſhall riſe, nor the Wind when it ſhall blow, ſo nor the Spirit of the Lord a time when he ſhall work.</item>
               </list>
               <p>We know not (as the wiſe man ſaid of ſowing ſeed, <hi>Eccleſs.</hi> 11.6.) whether our waiting on this or that, whether now or then, or when this or that ſhall be ſucceſsful to us; 'tis enough to quiet and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort us in our attentive waiting, that we have his <hi>ſic volo, ſic jubeo</hi> for it; and that we are at the right door. Man is for the ſhorteſt time, and God is for the fitteſt time; if we wait long and have not ſo quick an anſwer, yet we ſhall have a fuller anſwer; and when the mercy comes it will be ſweeter.</p>
               <p>You know that food be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo good, muſt have a time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:30413:61"/>for its concoction; it may be ſo in this preſent caſe, the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances muſt have time allowed for their operation. You find not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, that power over your corruptions and impetuous paſſions, not that increaſe of Grace, not that joy in the Holy Ghoſt, not that full aſſurance of his Love which is dearer and ſweeter to you than your very life; as was expected. Well, but work with diligence, and wait with patience; work I ſay, and be not ſlothful, wait and be not wilful; theſe (or ſome of them) are but one ſtep ſhort of Heaven; when you are gone thence you may have ſome ſmiles, after the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you may meet with more.</p>
               <p>There are ſome ſpecial ſeaſons in which he gives in aſſurances of his loves unto his ſervants.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Sometimes immediately after their Converſion; Babes muſt be fed with ſweet things; Lambs muſt be carry'd in the arms. The Soul at firſt is not able to bear
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:30413:61"/>harſhneſs; Parents are more fond of Children at two than at twenty, it was thus with the Prodigal.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sometimes when they are under ſome great afflictions; when <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was among the Captives by the River of <hi>Chebar,</hi> then the Heavens were opened, and he ſaw Viſions of God, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.1. When the way is foul below, he will have the Heavens ſerene and clear above; when his people have wormwood from the World, they ſhall have wine from God; no Nectar nor Ambroſia comparable. Under the greateſt Croſſes the ſweeteſt and greateſt Comforts. I appeal to your own obſervation and experience.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Sometimes before ſome emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent trial, ſome great temptation and extraordinary conflict. — <hi>Stephen</hi> ſaw the Heavens opened, and the Son of Man ſtanding on the right hand of God, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.56. But what followed, you ſee <hi>v.</hi> 59. <hi>They ran upon him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> caſt him out of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:30413:62"/>the City and ſtoned him till he died.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> was firſt wrapt up into the third Heaven, and heard (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,) <hi>words that neither might nor could be uttered.</hi> But then comes the meſſenger (Satan) to buffet him,<note place="margin"> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> caſu re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto, ut D. A. in Tact. Sacr. Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> paſſim.</note> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4, 7. A more eminent inſtance (becauſe of a more eminent perſon) is yet behind. No ſooner was our Lord baptized, at which time was heard that voice from Heaven, ſaying, <hi>This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed;</hi> but the Spirit leads him up into the Wilderneſs, and there the Devil tempts him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. <hi>ult. Ch.</hi> 4.1, 2.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Sometimes after ſome great croſſes; without the leaſt impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his Love or Wiſdom (on purpoſe to evacuate ſome peccant humour) he may, nay, does ſuffer his deareſt Children to lie under the black rod; none ſuffer</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Sorer, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.12.</item>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:30413:62"/>
                  <item>2. Sooner, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.9.</item>
                  <item>3. Surer, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.2. than they here.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The Sons of God are known by their Affections and Afflictions.</p>
               <p>Now the ſenſible manifeſtations of his love and favour he reſerves in great wiſdom (as Phyſitians do their choiceſt Cordials) and gives them after the Phyſick is over: After a ſharp and bitter Winter, the beſt and ſweeteſt Spring. But once more.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Sometimes when they are waiting upon him in his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, when they are in Prayer, the Spirit of the Lord comes in and whiſpers, Thou art mine. At the Sacrament, O what heart-enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have they in that! what beams of light and love have been darted in at his Table! what Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine comforts have they been filled with there?</p>
               <p>That 'tis often thus I need not prove, your own experience will
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:30413:63"/>contribute to the evidence of this Aſſertion.—But that it is ever thus, I may in no wiſe maintain: He is a great King, and Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty would and ſhould be waited on. It is good for a man to attend and wait on God in all his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments. Increaſe of grace, ſtrength and power againſt ſin, aſſurance of his love come too ſoon to that man, who thinks Gods time of ſending them is too long or late.</p>
               <p>I will ſhut up this Diſcourſe with that memorable paſſage of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> ch. 30.18. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will the Lord wait, that he may be gracious unto you, and therefore will he be exalted, that he may have mercy upon you; for the Lord is a God of Judgment. Bleſſed are all they that wait for him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that of <hi>Habakkuk. The vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is yet for an appointed time, but at the end it ſhall ſpeak, and not lie; though it tarry, wait for it, becauſe it will ſurely came, it will
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:30413:63"/>not tarry:</hi> So ſay I, the Sacrament is for an appointed time; but in due time the Spirit of the Lord will ſpeak peace, though he tarry wait for him, becauſe he will ſurely come, and give in more life and light, and grace and peace, yea joy without meaſure and joy without mixture.—<hi>Now to God the Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>The End of the ſecond Sermon.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:30413:64"/>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="sermon">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:30413:64"/>
               <head>The Third SERMON</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>On Micah 2.7.</hi>
                     </bibl> Is the Spirit of the Lord ſtraitned?<note place="margin">
                        <hi>July</hi> the 27th. 1673</note> Do not my words do good to him that walketh uprightly?</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>was excellent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel which an eminent <hi>German</hi> Divine once hinted to a young Preacher,<note place="margin">Luther:</note> 
                  <hi>Cum vides populum attentiſſime andientem, conclude, eo alacriores redibunt.</hi> When you obſerve the people hearing moſt attentively, conclude your diſcourſe quickly, and they will return with more alacrity. This numerous Aſſembly gives in evidence enough thereof.</p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:30413:65"/>
               <p>The Logical reſolution of theſe words you heard before, and the obſervations thence deduced. The Propoſitions under debate cleared; and ſeveral Queries reſolved; we are now upon the Sixth. 'Tis this.</p>
               <p>Q. 6. <hi>What courſe ſhall a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian take that he may have the Spirit of the Lord to do him good by this Ordinance of the Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Directions are many; we have diſpatcht four, and now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the fifth in order; which is this.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Be thankful to God for what good you have any time got by this precious Ordinance: For, <hi>Gratiarum actio eſt ad plus dandum invitatio.</hi> He who can cordially praiſe him for a little life and ſtrength, and grace, and peace, ſhall ſoon have more than a little to thank him for; the moſt expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious way to get what at any
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:30413:65"/>time we want, is to be grateful for that we already have; others have only the ſhell, you have had the kernel, they nothing but bones, and you the marrow. Have you had any quicknings, any refreſhings from the Spirit of the Lord at this Table, then ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Bleſs the Lord O my Soul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Sacrament in its full extent compriſeth two things.</p>
               <p>A viſible and an inviſible part; the Schools call that, <hi>Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> this, <hi>rem Sacramenti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Excuſe this ſhort digreſſion, pray, upon this occaſion: If they of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church will ſtand their ground, and be true to their own Principles, it will appear to every vulgar capacity that they have none of this Sacrament amongſt 'em. For, before they take and eat, the viſible part is gone, both being converted into the Body and Blood of Chriſt; for thus their Council (or rather their Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy at <hi>Trent,</hi> or if you will, that
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:30413:66"/>tranſcendent thing call'd <hi>Pope</hi>) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines Tranſubſtantiation; 'Tis a change of the whole ſubſtance of the Bread into the whole ſubſtance of the Body of Chriſt, and of the Wine into his Blood, <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 13. <hi>Can.</hi> 2: and this change is wrought, ere any take or eat. This is a novel opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a new Article of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Creed; of the ſame date with <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth, without any baſis or foundation in the Holy Scripture,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num de Euch. lib.</hi> 1 <hi>cap.</hi> 34. <hi>pag.</hi> 419. See that unanſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able piece of Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> in 8. Books againſt the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Maſs.</note> as their own <hi>Scotus</hi> and <hi>Camera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſis,</hi> and <hi>Cajetan</hi> confeſs. Nay, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf ſays, <hi>Non tam ex Evangelio, quam ex Eccleſiae au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate constat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to return: When this change is made, where is that outward and viſible part, which their School-Divines call <hi>Sacramentum?</hi> —</p>
               <p>But have (my Beloved) by a lively faith fed on, and been ſtrengthned by this Heavenly Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na? then take heed of unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs:<note place="margin">2. Chron. 32.25.</note> O remember that [But] <hi>But Hezekiah remembred not to render
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:30413:66"/>unto the Lord according to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit done unto him.</hi> O what a blot was that [But] in that good Kings ſcutcheon. When you come next to the Lords Table, bring Harps in your hands, (they are emblems of praiſe.<note place="margin">Heb. 5.8.</note>) The Spirit of the Lord will not, I had almoſt ſaid, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, but do you good, if humble and thankful for what good he hath done you already.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Grieve not the Spirit of the Lord, if you would have him to do you good by this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. He is a delicate perſon, if you grieve him, he may, nay will grieve you. Has he begun in love to melt and mollifie your flinty hearts, to increaſe your graces, to ſpeak peace unto your Souls? if you now diſtaſte him, he may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw and leave the work at a ſad and long ſtand; you may hear no more of him of many days, nay, months or years. Grieve not the holy Spirit of God; why? <hi>Paul</hi> gives his <hi>Epheſian</hi> Converts a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:30413:67"/>reaſon why they ſhould not, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.30. thereby <hi>ye are ſea;led to the day of redemption;</hi> if you do, you may be the firſt will rue it; you ſhall be without the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſings and ſealings of the Spirit for a longer time than you are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But how or when is the Spirit of the Lord grieved?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer briefly.</p>
               <p>When his Ordinances are not attended, his commands are not obeyed, his comforts are not prized, his graces are not acted and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; his aſſiſtance in duties is not deſired; his motions are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded. — In a word, if you will not have the Spirit for your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor, you cannot expect him long to be your Comforter; lay not a bar in his way, and he ſtill will do you good by this holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, Heighten your hopes and expectations when you are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this Ordinance, if you would
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:30413:67"/>have the Spirit of the Lord to do you good by it.</p>
               <p>There is much good laid up for you, come on then, Sirs, and quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken your hopes; great expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from God greatly honour the greatneſs of God, and wonderfully advantage you. 'Tis as diſpleaſing to him, and as prejudicial to you, when you believe little as when you do little. Open your mouths and hearts wide; you have not only Gods power for it, but his promiſe too, to fill you.</p>
               <p>One reaſon why you receive ſo little good at it, is becauſe you look for ſo little good by it; when your faith is very weak, and your expectations are very low, you do what in you is to hinder the Spirit of the Lord from doing you good. But ſurely when you have a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Prayer, and your hopes are high, theſe are pledges to you, that he hath a purpoſe to do you good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great was wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully well pleas'd with <hi>Anaxarchus</hi>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:30413:68"/>the Philoſopher,<note place="margin">Plut.</note> when he deſir'd an hundred Talents of his Treaſurer.<note place="margin">Apoph.</note> He does well (ſays he) in asking it, and underſtands his friend aright, who hath one both willing and able to give him ſo great a gift. The ſame Author relates the like of that Kings munificence and bounty to his Favourite <hi>Perillus,</hi> who askt but ten,<note place="margin">Plut.</note> but the King gave him fifty Talents. The great God allows his people to ask great things, nay com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them to believe and hope for mighty things; to covet earneſtly the beſt; if thus you do, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord will ſurely do you good; you ſhall not ſeek nor hope in vain.</p>
               <p>Well then, when you addreſs your ſelves to this Ordinance, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what great things Chriſt hath purchas'd for you; what great things are there propoſed, and God hath promiſed to you; and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate your prayers by, and raiſe your hopes to the riches of his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and greatneſs of his mercies.</p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:30413:68"/>
               <p>Some look for good by this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; but what good, or for what 'tis good they know not; or they look for that good in it which God never intended to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey by it. Others have their hopes fixt on the right object, their ends are right too, but they have not a lively Hope. In ſhort, if the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord be not preſent, the Sacrament is but a gaudy pageant; 'tis the ſpirit in the Word that cauſeth efficacy; in Prayer that cauſeth prevalency; in this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance that cauſeth proficiency: But then muſt we have an active Faith, a ſtrong and lively Hope.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, Lament over the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, dullneſs, the deadneſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preparedneſs of your Hearts for this bleſſed Ordinance: When one hath taken Phyſick and it doth not ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, ſomething is preſcribed and uſed to quicken it: A ſincere ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for your former careleſneſs and deadneſs may much conduce to your future proficiency.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:30413:69"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>They ſhall come with weeping,</hi> ſays the Prophet <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.9. Tears drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping from a mournful eye and griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Heart, are like Water drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping from the Roſes, very ſweet, fragrant and ſoveraign. <hi>Mary</hi> ſtood at Chriſts feet weeping, <hi>Luc.</hi> 7.38. Could we kneel at the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble weeping (and is not the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt poſture fitteſt for miſerable ſinners?) could we weep tears of blood for our ſcarlet, crimſon, bloody ſins, acting her part, we might hope for her portion, a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pardon, and that ſealed in this Ordinance.</p>
               <p>We pity weeping perſons, and do them good; Tears melt our Hearts,<note place="margin">Pſal 6.8.</note> and though ſilent, yet they are prevalent Orators; when you are in ſuch a melting frame, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd by ſerious meditation on your ſins and Chriſts ſufferings; on his bitter paſſions for you, and moſt tender affections to you; then, lo, then's a ſeaſon for the Spirit of the Lord to do you good by this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance:
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:30413:69"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſays <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom:</hi> Weep out your eyes for the loſs of lands or friends, all your tears will nothing avail you; but in this caſe they may, nay will much.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, Go out in the power and might of the Spirit of the Lord to this Ordinance; you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not relie on men or means too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, or on him too much; you ſhould depend on him though you had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver tried him, but having tried him, you are now under greater obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to depend on him. Royal and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious is that reſolution of the Prophet <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 71.16. <hi>I will go in the strength of the Lord God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Inpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>tus. <hi>q.d.</hi> Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> unius vir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</note> Let us write after his Copy:— remember; <hi>ejus eſt benedicere, cujus eſt inſtituere.</hi>—Alas all our light is darkneſs, our ſtrength weakneſs, and our wiſdom fooliſhneſs. <hi>Fruſtra nititur qui non innititur;</hi> that man labours in vain, who labours and
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:30413:70"/>yet relies not upon the Spirit of the Lord; if the Spirit help you to pray, he will alſo help you to ſpeed; and if he help you to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for, and to go out in his might unto this Ordinance, ſurely he will do you good by it; I will cloſe up this with that excellent paſſage of Saint <hi>Cyprian, de Bapt. Solus ſpiritus rem ſacramenti no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis confert.</hi> Or that famous ſpeech of the School-Doctors,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Sacramenta
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>ex ſimilitudine reprae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentant.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>ex inſtitutione ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sed, ex virtute Christi ſanctificant.</hi> Or with that of <hi>Proſper</hi> in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to <hi>Demetrius,</hi> ſpeaking of the holy Sacraments; <hi>Forma adhibetur per humani miniſterii obſequium, virtus autem per Divini ſpiritus praeſtatur effectum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tenthly, Once more. Walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, and the Spirit of the Lord will do you good by this Ordinance; you have his promiſe for it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:30413:70"/>
                  <hi>The Lord will give grace and glory.</hi> Grace, that's the beſt thing that you can have on Earth.— Glory, that's the long and the ſhort of what you ſhall have in Heaven. <hi>No good thing will he withhold from them that walk uprightly.</hi> Let a thred of uprightneſs run thorough the whole web of your lifes; and then you are ſure
<list>
                     <item>(1) of being ſafe in this world, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.9. Men may kill you but they cannot hurt you.</item>
                     <item>(2) of being ſaved in the other world: But of this anon.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Follow theſe few Directions, and I dare be the Prophet to foretel you good by this holy Inſtitution.</p>
               <p>I proceed now unto the ſeventh Query.</p>
               <p>Q. 7. <hi>What ſhall a Christian do who hath ſound ſome good at, in, and by, or after this precious Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, from the powerful workings of the ſpirit of the Lord?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will hint a few Directions to
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:30413:71"/>you in anſwer to this Query; the amplification of 'em I leave to your private Meditations. They are Ten or Eleven.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Walk Thankefully.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hath it been the day of his power, let it be a day for his praiſe; you have had news from Heaven, let the Heavens hear good from you.</p>
               <p>Though you have not got all the good you deſired, yet bleſs God for this, that you have got more than you have deſerved. And bleſs God for this too, that you have a deſire ſtill to get more. O deſpiſe not the day of ſmall things. Say, Lord, who or what am I that the Spirit of the Lord ſhould conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend or ſtoop ſo low as to breathe upon my Soul, to blow upon my Garden, and cauſe the Spices there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to flow forth; who am I that he ſhould cauſe this Ordinance to work for my ſpiritual and eternal good, when others eat and drink Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to themſelves? I will write my ſelf an eternal debter to free Grace,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:30413:71"/>for 'tis that, that fitted me for, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted me to and benefited me by this ſacred Ordinance. I will ever remember that golden ſentence of Saint <hi>Auſtin, Hoc totum hominis est, curare ut anima non ſit ingrata Deo:</hi> This is the whole buſineſs of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man, To take care that his Soul be not unthankful to his God.</p>
               <p>Have I received any light or life, or increaſe of grace and peace, I will remember to my dying day, though 'tis wrought in me, yet 'twas not wrought by me. <hi>Non no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Domine, non nobis;</hi> Not unto us, Lord, not unto us; Becauſe not by us, Lord, not by us, but by the Spirit of the Lord of Hoſts. Though I cannot praiſe thee ſo much as I ſhould, yet will I praiſe thee as much as I can.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sacramenta Judaeorum umbra Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianorum. <hi>Aug:</hi> Enar: in <hi>Pſal: 37:</hi> nobis <hi>38:</hi>
                  </note>At the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Paſſover was ſung the 113. and ſome following <hi>Pſalms;</hi> and this they call'd the Great <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujah;</hi> And the Sacraments of the <hi>Jews</hi> were but ſhadows unto ours.
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:30413:72"/>In every thing we muſt give thanks, but for this eſpecially; others ſtand without, you are admitted into the Preſence-chamber of the great King. They feed on husks and traſh, you on the hidden Manna. <hi>My fleſh</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>is meat indeed, and my blood is drink indeed.</hi> All other food com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd with this is <hi>cibi tantummodo umbra &amp; vana imago;</hi> as <hi>Cameron</hi> ſpeaks; all ſhadow, no ſubſtance. To a worthy Receiver the choiceſt of mercies and bleſſings are here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited: one calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Food made up all of Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving.</hi> And having taſted ſo much, nay drunk ſo deep of the cup of bleſſing, does it not concern you now to ſing, Glory be to the Holy Ghoſt? That praiſe is due to God from every Creature in the World, and from every corner of the world, I need not prove; but 'tis not come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for any but ſuch as you, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.1. 'Tis a garment that ſuites none but Saints, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.3. You read there of the garment of praiſe.—The
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:30413:72"/>
                  <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Doctors have a ſaying, <hi>That the World ſubſiſts by three Pillars, the Law, the Worſhip of God, and Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs.</hi> O let the high Praiſes of God be now and for ever in your lips and lives.</p>
               <p>Hath the good Spirit of the Lord gone out before you in love and mercy? Do you follow him now in praiſe and duty. 'Tis the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Saints in Heaven to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy God; and 'tis their only buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Heaven to bleſs God; and is it not your wiſdom as well as duty, to be daily doing that on Earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides which you ſhall have nothing to do to all Eternity in Heaven? <hi>Hoſanna's</hi> here and <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> hereafter.</p>
               <p n="2">(2) <hi>Walk charitably.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do all the good you poſſibly can for the Spirit of the Lord, and for the people of the Lord. I know your goodneſs extendeth not to God, but let it the more to the Saints. Yet you may plead for and vindicate his honour; which is by
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:30413:73"/>many now laid in the duſt; many father their errors and blaſphemies on the Spirit, laying them at his door, as if he were not the Spirit of Truth.</p>
               <p>There are four ſorts of men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>(1) Some who are all for Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, not eying at all the Spirit of the Lord for his teachings.</item>
                  <item>(2) Some are all for the Spirit, Sanſ-ordinance men; caſting of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, the Miniſtry of the Word, and this bleſſed Sacrament.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Beza in</hi> 1 Cor. 1.12</note> As <hi>Beza</hi> ſaid, ſo ſhall I, <hi>Hoc Peſtilentiſſimo morbo utinam nulli hodie laborarent.</hi> Oh that none had this Plague-ſore now.</item>
                  <item>(3) Others (and not a few) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther regard the Spirit, nor men nor means; nothing but <hi>mundum &amp; fundum.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>(4) Only the ſincere Chriſtian is for all; and he is the man to whom I addreſs this counſel; —if you eſpouſe not his cauſe who ſhall? if in your ſtations as Magiſtrates, as Miniſters, as Chriſtians you plead
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:30413:73"/>not for it who will? But—walk charitably towards men; that's the duty I would preſs on you.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Has the Spirit of the Lord done you good? do you now all the good you can to others; ſhew your love to God by your love to your needy Brethren, and your love to them by works of mercy. Acts of charity do not impoveriſh but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich. Perhaps the Purſe may be ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but your Crown will be heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Who ever heard or read of a man that liv'd charitably that died miſerably.<note place="margin">Non memini me legiſſe malâ morte mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>, qui libenter opera cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercuit: <hi>Hieron:</hi> Moriſon <hi>in his</hi> Itini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary:</note> 
                  <hi>Hierom</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Nepotian</hi> tells us he never did; nor did the royal Prophet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.25, 26.</p>
               <p>One tells us of a fountain of Salt in <hi>Germany,</hi> of which all the poor about it had Salt-water freely for their uſe, but when once it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd them, it loſt its vertue. If once you harden your Hearts againſt, or hide your faces from thoſe pale fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and withered cheeks, and maim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed arms; from thoſe who have no
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:30413:74"/>bread to eat, nor where to lay their heads; well may the Spirit of the Lord ſuſpend his influences at the next Communion, and then it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not heal nor ſeal, nor do you good. What greater incentive to ſhew mercy to others than a due ſenſe of mercies received from God? Do good to all as you are of ability, and have opportunity, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to the houſhold of Faith.</p>
               <p n="3">(3) <hi>Walk contentedly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Have you received good and much good at the Lords Table, then be not ſo full of complaints if you have little of the worlds goods: Is your grace increaſed, have you got more aſſurance of your Lords love? do not murmur though your Corn and Wine and other matters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe not: Whilſt thoſe put glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into your Hearts let not the want of theſe cauſe ſadneſs to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in your faces. <hi>It is enough</hi> (ſays <hi>Jacob</hi>) <hi>Joſeph is alive.</hi> So ſay you, It is enough, the Spirit of the Lord is alive, and hath enlivened and
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:30413:74"/>ſealed,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and comforted me at and by this precious Ordinance. <hi>Shew us the Father</hi> (ſays <hi>Philip</hi>) <hi>and it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth us.</hi> The ſight of God without riches or honours, or lands, or friends ſhould ſatisfie your Souls. Having food and raiment you ſhould be content; well,<note place="margin">Having food, not fine fare: Raiments not Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</note> and you have both; nay much more; <hi>viz.</hi> the Mediatory Righteouſneſs of Chriſt to deck and adorn you, and his precious Body and Blood to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh you. And whatever afflictions you meet with in or from the World, ſtill be contented. They ſay, whatever betides a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> he will not change his pace; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever troubles betide you, let no change appear in your Face. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God give or take; whether he ſtroke or ſtrike;<note place="margin">Nimis deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus es frater, ſi &amp; hic vis gaudere cum mundo &amp; poſthac regnare cum Chriſto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Hierom.</hi>
                  </note> whether men hum or hiſs, fret not your ſelves; ſhall you receive good from the hand of God: What, all good and no evil? you are too delicate, if you would have two Heavens, one here, and another yonder above the Clouds.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:30413:75"/>
               <p n="4">(4) <hi>Walk Compaſſionately.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Have you taſted there of the Lords graciouſneſs, can you tell of the great things the Spirit of the Lord hath by that Ordinance done for your Souls; then be not ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilious and cenſorious, but candid and ingenuous towards others who come thence without any ſenſe of increaſed grace, or evidences of his love and favour, <hi>Job</hi> 6.14. To him that is afflicted (melted in the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of Affliction) pity ſhould be ſhewed. Is it not enough that God doth grieve them by the ſuſpenſion of his influences, but muſt you add unto their ſorrows? and why ſhould you inſult over them? Are you Saints, ſo are they<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Though they walk in darkneſs yet they are chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Light. Know and do your duty; pray for them and pray with them. Can you go from promiſe to promiſe, and ſay, Theſe are mine. Or from Ordinance to Ordinance, and ſay, By all theſe the Spirit of the Lord hath done, and ſtill is do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:30413:75"/>me good. Well, be you thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but be not proud nor ſupercili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; be not high-minded but fear: At the next Communion he may vail his Face from you, and reveal his love to them, whom now you brow-beat, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.6, 7. He may turn your Wine into water, and their water into wine, he may do them much more, and you much leſs good at the next addreſs you make unto the Lords Table. Let not ſuch as are high and rich in grace and peace cenſure them that are poor and low, and do not you that are low envy them that are high; but bear ye one anothers burdens, rejoyce in one anothers Graces, mutually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the work of Holineſs, be leſs in cenſuring and more in praying;<note place="margin">Oret Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolus pro plebe, oret plebs pro Apoſtolo, pro ſe omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a membra orent, caput pro omnibus interpellat: <hi>Aug.</hi> in <hi>Pſal. 38.</hi>
                  </note> the Paſtor for the People, the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for their Paſtor; one member for another; ever remembring that Jeſus Chriſt our merciful high Prieſt is pleading and interceding for us all.</p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:30413:76"/>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">Egregia laus non modo non ſatiſcere, ſed indies proficere in melius: <hi>Grot:</hi> in <hi>Rev:</hi> 2: 19:</note>(5) <hi>Walk fruitfully.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Make it your buſineſs to do all the good you can: Wherefore doth the Spirit of the Lord at any time, or by any means do you good, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make you better, and to ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you to do better? Go then and abound in the work of the Lord; let your laſt be more than your firſt; more for quantity, better for quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Be filled with the fruits of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,<note place="margin">This Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance concerns the Soul; may be the laſt, is the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of Chriſt, &amp; is a good gale for Heaven: Study then to be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful:</note> which are by Jeſus Chriſt unto the glory and praiſe of God. Be more vigorous in every holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; more zealous for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods Glory. Follow the Lord fully, faithfully and chearfully. Study how you may anſwer his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations from you, his diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to you, and the many obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are upon you. Hath he done more for you, do you the more for him; or your anſwer and account at the laſt day will be ſad indeed. You love to ſee every thing you have fruitful; much more doth the Spirit of the Lord love to ſee you ſo. O
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:30413:76"/>how happy were we, yea, <hi>Foelices ter &amp; amplius,</hi> might it but as truly be ſaid of us, as it was of <hi>Joſeph, Joſeph is a fruitful Bough.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 49.22.</note> Natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts ſay of the <hi>Pomecitron,</hi> that it bears fruit at all times of the year; this is the Emblem of an Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Communicant.—As a plant differs from a ſtone by vegetation, and a Beaſt differs from a plant by ſenſe; and a Man differs from a Beaſt by ſpeech and reaſon; ſo ſhould a Communicant differ from other men by fruitfulneſs. Come then and ſpread your branches, ſend forth your ſpices as Aromatick Trees in <hi>Lebanon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt chides a little Faith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.31. but admires and applauds a great Faith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer. 11.16 Joh. 15.8. Mat. 25: 30:</hi> Non tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de non ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vato, ſed de non aucto munere damnabun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: <hi>Profp:</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>O woman great is thy Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Scholars are not at eaſe till they have taken all their Degrees, though it coſt them dear; and why ſhould Chriſtians till they come to a <hi>Non ultra?</hi> Our bleſſed Saviour did on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly two terrible wonders; the one
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:30413:77"/>was the drowning of the Swine, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. and yet that was only done by his permiſſion. The other was his curſing and blaſting of the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Fig-tree, and that was ſymboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal; not done in ſpleen to the Tree, but only to manifeſt his indignation againſt an unfruitful profeſſion. Let us view that Text,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar. 11.13</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſubaudi <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ubi enim erat tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus erat ficuum; vel tempeſtivae ac maturae trant ficus. Accentus enim ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinctiones neglige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</note> 
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 11.13. <hi>See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Fig-tree afar off, having leaves he came; if haply he might find any thing thereon, but when he came to it he found nothing but leaves. For the time of Figs was not yet.</hi> You will ſay, was not this a cruel act? or unreaſonable? had it been a time for Figs, the blaſting of it had been reaſonable and juſt. I anſwer, the words in the original are not rightly comma'd and accented; if they were, they would run thus, <hi>For where he was, it was a time of Figs,</hi> as one well obſerves; <hi>viz.</hi> Learned <hi>Heinſius</hi> on <hi>Mark</hi> 11.13.</p>
               <p>You have been (ſome of you at leaſt) three or four days together at the Lords Table upon this ſignal
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:30413:77"/>and ſpecial occaſion; beſides your Communions in courſe, every firſt Lords-day in the Month. You are planted in a fruitful Hill, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 15.1. The Sun-beams of mercies, Zions ſilver-drops have fallen on you; you hear more of God and from God in one day, than ſome thouſands in the world have done in all their lives. Theſe are your enjoyments, what now are your improvements? your receipts are high, let not your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns be low; if he find you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fruit, he will leave you without excuſe: Nay, he may deal with you as with that barren Fig-tree, blaſt and not bleſs you. But my hopes are and my prayers ſhall be for you, as St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s were for the <hi>Philippians,</hi> that your Faith and Love, and all your Graces may abound,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.9.</note>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, yet more and more.</p>
               <p n="6">(6) <hi>Walk cloſely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Keep cloſe (that's my meaning) to this precious Ordinance where you have ſo happily met with all this good from the Spirit of the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:30413:78"/>Lord; thoſe ſweet experiences you have had of his quickening and ſtrengthening influences ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage you (if it will not others) to a more conſtant and diligent atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon him in this ſolemn Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance.</p>
               <p>The Queſtion once was,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.12.</note> 
                  <hi>How cameſt thou in hither not having on the Wedding garment?</hi> The Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I muſt invert, and put it thus to you. Having on the Wedding-gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, how comes it now to paſs that you go out? Do veſtures or geſtures, or the prayers of the Church deter or drive you hence? would you not complain of us, ſhould we excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate or caſt you out? and is it well done in you, thus to caſt out your ſelves? Have you no need of this Ordinance? if ſo, why do you turn your backs, and by your exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples diſcourage others; you ſhould rather come and cry to others, Come ye and let us go up to the Mountain of the Lord, to the Houſe of the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and he will teach us of his
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:30413:78"/>ways, and feed us with the bread of life; and do us good by his holy Spirit. Excellent is that paſſage of St. <hi>Austin</hi> in his firſt Book <hi>de vera Relig. cap.</hi> 6. where he ſhews the conſtancy of the Godly for publick Aſſemblies, againſt Conventicles; a word it is you may obſerve of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 1200 years ſtanding upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; <hi>ſine ulla conventiculorum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatione uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad mortem defenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; Testimonio juvantes eam fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, quam in Eccleſia Catholica prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicari ſciunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is an Obſervation which ſome have concerning the ſimpathy of Plants, that ſome plants will bear better near other Trees, than when they grow alone; they inſtance in the myrtle and the Olive: Sure I am 'tis true in Divinity; when the Saints aſſociate in theſe publique Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, and ſit together at the Lords Table, they thrive moſt. Therefore having had ſuch experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the Spirits influences in this ſacred and ſolemn Ordinance, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:30413:79"/>not the Aſſembling of your ſelves together; but exhort one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other to a more conſtant and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious attendance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24, 26.</p>
               <p n="7">(7) <hi>Walk chearfully.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let your Hearts be wonderfully enlarged now in rejoycing in God. <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord always,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, I ſay, rejoyce,</hi> Phil. 4.4.</p>
               <p>The Ingemination of the charge intimates three things,
<list>
                     <item>The Neceſſity,</item>
                     <item>The Difficulty,</item>
                     <item>The Excellency,</item>
                  </list>
of the Duty.</p>
               <p>Joy ſuits no perſon ſo well as a Saint; no day ſo well as the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath; no duty ſo well as a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; no Ordinance better I am ſure.</p>
               <p>Has he made you fruitful, then be it your care to be joyful.</p>
               <p>The Rabbins have a ſaying, <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus ſanctus non quieſcit niſi ſuper Hilarem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heinſ. <hi>in</hi> N. T.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Has the Spirit of the Lord been doing you good this day or at any time by this Ordinance, has he been
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:30413:79"/>as a refiners fire,<note place="margin">Non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Dux ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentem mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litem.</note> burning up the droſs, and making your Graces ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle like gold in the furnace? are his ſignatures and engraving upon your Souls: Then ſay, This is the day which the Lord hath made, a good day, a day of mirth and gladneſs, we will be glad and rejoyce there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Now ſing the <hi>Magnificat, My Soul doth magnifie the Lord, and, &amp;c.</hi> None have that call, none have that cauſe to rejoyce as you. 'Tis a ſaying too trite, unleſs it were more true,
<q>Spiritus Calviniſticus est Spiritus Melancholicus.</q>
Moſt think they ſhall never have merry day, if once they devote themſelves to Gods ſervice, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, though but in the duties which concern this Ordinance. But your chearfulneſs will confute their ignorant and malicious cenſures; you may aſſure them from your own experience, that there is more true and ſolid joy and comfort to be had in and by this precious Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance;
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:30413:80"/>more peace in having Communion with God, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications from the Spirit of the Lord at his Table, than in the moſt luſcious acts of ſin, or thoſe brutiſh pleaſures the World affords. Tell them the fruits of the Spirit are joy and peace, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts are the golden Pot and the Manna, the Nectar and Ambroſia of a Saint: But their pleaſures are mixt with mortiferous ingredients; at the beſt like Wine that runs dregs, and whilſt they have a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful countenance, they cannot deny (if they will ſpeak all the truth) but they have a corroding and chiding Conſcience.</p>
               <p n="8">(8) <hi>Walk perſeveringly.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Pſal. 119.112.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Walk on in the ſtrength of this food (as <hi>Elias</hi> did of his) till you come to the Mount of God; be not weary of, nor weary in well-doing. Blood ennobles, and Learning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorns, but 'tis perſeverance in the way and worſhip, and favour of God that crowns all. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. Only the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:30413:80"/>through-Chriſtian is in Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the true Chriſtian. The fixed Stars are few; in our age many are falling Stars; they are not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>ſtedfaſt in Godlineſs;</hi> they are like <hi>Reuben, unſtable as water;</hi> an Element hardly kept within bounds. But hold faſt that which you have; good things are not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly got, therefore it concerns you to hold 'em faſt; and many good things are eaſily loſt, and therefore it is your wiſdom to hold 'em faſt. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. <hi>If any man draw back, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surely the good you ſay you have got at this Ordinance is ſuch as you highly eſtimate, and perhaps it coſt you many tears and prayers, then be the more choice of it; it will ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten your paſſage to the Heavenly Canaan. Some notions concerning the Perſeverance of the Saints were lately hinted. I ſhall now ſay no more of this, but leave you in the meditation of two famous Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Job</hi> 17.9. <hi>The righteous ſhall
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:30413:81"/>hold on his way, and he that hath clean hands ſhall be ſtronger and stronger.</hi> Prov. 4.18. <hi>The path of the just is as the ſhining light that ſhineth more and more unto the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">(9) <hi>Walk Heavenly:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment calls for an Heav'n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>An earthly Saint is a Soleciſm or contradiction; therefore has the Spirit of the Lord done you good by it that he might engage you to live more to him, and to live more with him; more for Heaven, and more in Heaven. Every manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his love unto the Soul ſhould raiſe it above the World. And if you do not live much above the World, you live much beneath your Principles, and priviledges, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath your ſelves. O let your diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and affections, your operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and communications, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations, and expectations be more Heavenly! The good which God ſends you in by his Spirit is to fetch your hearts up to him. Grace in the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:30413:81"/>heart (like fire on the hearth) tends <hi>(ſurſum)</hi> upwards; it makes the Soul to mount or ſparkle upwards in divine breathings and ejaculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The man whoſe heart is not in Heaven before himſelf comes there is never like to come there. O let your thoughts and delights, your hopes and comforts be above the world. Be content with the worſt of it, but be not ſatisfied with the beſt of it; for every crumb you ſhould be thankful, but with Crowns and Diadems you muſt not take up.</p>
               <p>The more ſweet you have met with at this Supper, the more bitter ſhould the world be unto you for ever after.<note place="margin">Ludov. Vives <hi>on</hi> Aug. l. <hi>18:</hi> cap: <hi>54.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cui dulceſcit Chriſtus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mareſcit mundus.</hi> When our bleſſed Saviour was a dying, the whole World was in obſcurity, 'twas mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night dark at Noon-day, and the Stars were viſible. This Sacrament is a lively repreſentation and ſolemn Commemoration of his Death; when you are about it and gone from it, let the world be darkneſs to you. I
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:30413:82"/>will leave St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his Counſel with you, <hi>Toto animo odi &amp; damna quod diligit mundus: Tanquam mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus a labe &amp; affectu illius te ſepara;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſtolaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lib.</hi> 4. Floriano.</note> 
                  <hi>ſicut ſepultus nil habeas carum de ſaeculo, tanquam defunct us omni ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reno te abdica negotio; contemne vivens, quae poſt mortem habere non poteris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">(10) <hi>Walk watchfully,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>uprightly.</hi> As it is not enough that you be and do good for a day or two be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you come to the Sacrament, but your care muſt be to walk upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; ſo it muſt be your care when you are gone thence to walk thus. <hi>Go then and ſin no more,</hi> Joh. 5.14. no more ſo wilfully, ſo prefumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly. To ſin after a Sacrament is to ſin with a witneſs. To ſin againſt cleareſt light and deareſt love pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokes exceedingly, and yours will be found of this nature.</p>
               <p>To provoke God in a Wilderneſs is not ſo bad or ſad as to provoke God in a Paradiſe. 'Twas an aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Eves</hi> ſin to liſten to the whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perings
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:30413:82"/>of the Serpent when placed there; 'tis ſo for you who have been ſealed with the holy Spirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, now to liſten to the deluſions of that lying Spirit.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Enar. in</hi> Pſal. 29</note> 
                  <hi>Adam in ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>core</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>) <hi>eſt cautior, quam Adam in Paradiſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sacramentum eſt juramentum,</hi> every wilful iniquity now comes little ſhort of perjury.</p>
               <p>There are ſome ſins which the fallen Angels were never guilty of; they ſinned not againſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of God; <hi>non expectavit An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelos;</hi> they ſuffered immediately as they had ſinned. Nor againſt the tenders and offers of Grace; the golden Scepter was never held out, nor pardon offer'd to them. Nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Death and Paſſion of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; he died not for them; if now we ſin, not out of weakneſs, but out of wilfulneſs; our ſins will be found ſuch as the Devils them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are not guilty of. What higher priviledg is or can mortal man be capable of on this ſide Heaven, than
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:30413:83"/>to be feaſted at the Lords Table with theſe Heavenly viands. Now the greatneſs of the Priviledg adds to the greatneſs of the crime;<note place="margin">Ubi ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mior praero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gativa, ibi major cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa. <hi>Salv. de Gub. Dei</hi> lib. <hi>4,</hi> pag, <hi>128.</hi>
                  </note> your ſins after a Sacrament cannot take Chriſt from you, but they may take reſt from you, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.3. They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take Grace from you, but they may take peace from you; God may break your bones and leave you long in the dark; you may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver recover that comfort and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance which you had before. Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men have their Heaven here, and their Hell hereafter; and ſome good men have their Hell here, and their Heaven hereafter.</p>
               <p>Now, Sirs, you have been at the Lords Table, you have ſeen what Sin coſt Chriſt; what buffetings, what bruiſings, what woundings, what bleedings; and ſhall not this engage us to greater circumſpection to our dying day? having received ſo much good from the Spirit of the Lord ſhall not we watch our ways, and keep our Hearts and Eyes,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:30413:83"/>and Tongues,<note place="margin">Obſtrue quin<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtras (i.e. quin<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus) ut lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. <hi>Prov. Arab.</hi>
                  </note> and All with more care and diligence? If <hi>Iſrael</hi> play the Harlot, yet <hi>Judah</hi> muſt not tranſgreſs. Having now been at ſuch an Ordinance as this, ſhall we again return to break his Commandments? Every mercy is a motive to duty; and to walk circumſpectly, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, wiſely, uprightly is one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſpute, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.15. <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.37. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.5. Let not the increaſe of our mercies be the decreaſe of our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Though we walk in, yet let us not walk after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit of the Lord, who by this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution hath done us all this good.</p>
               <p>Once more: <hi>Walk Penitently.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You muſt renew your repentance as well after, as before this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. Call to remembrance the deadneſs of your Hearts, the cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your Love, the unactiveneſs of your Faith, the many wandrings and diſtractions of your minds and ſpirits when about this duty. There are ſome ſpecial ſeaſons for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of repentance.—As,</p>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:30413:84"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1. When you are a dying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though we muſt not defer it till death, yet we muſt be ſure to renew it at death. We ſhould take our fill of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance before we take our leave of repentance: thus St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> did, he caus'd the Penitential Pſalms to be fixt before him on the wall, and as he lay in bed he wept and read, and read and wept abundantly; <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuebatur &amp; legebat, &amp; jugitr ac u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertim flebat;</hi> as <hi>Poſſidonius</hi> relates it, <hi>De vita Aug. cap.</hi> 31.</item>
                  <item>2. And when you are ſuffering for God or from God, under ſome great afflictions; though repentance muſt not be limited to a time of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, yet it muſt be renewed in a time of affliction; for Gods end and deſign in and by them is not to break our backs, but to break our hearts. Once more,</item>
                  <item>3. When you are a doing, or have done any great and more ſolemn duty. What, is there nothing now you have been at this Ordinance to renew your repentance for? was
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:30413:84"/>all ſo well done? did corruption act ſo weakly, and Grace ſo vigor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and ſtrongly? was the evil ſpirit ſo chained and reſtrained? and did the good Spirit of the Lord ſo enlarge, enliven and ſtrengthen? is there no need of praying over your prayers again; of repenting that your repentance was no more Evangelical? — Did you thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider (as you ought) your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viors Paſſion in the matter and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of it; in its bitter ingredients and heightning circumſtances of it? or your own ſins, the meritorious cauſe of it? You had ſome light a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this in your heads; but was it attended with power and efficacy upon your hearts? for the cleareſt notions without ſuitable impreſſions will not advantage you.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And thus have we diſpatcht the counſels which concern you Saints, and alſo reſolv'd the ſeventh Query. If thus you walk, you will much honour the Spirit of the Lord; who is the great Agent in your Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:30413:85"/>Illumination, Converſion; and in your proficiency by this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred inſtitution. And as you are concern'd to honour the Son for what he hath done without, ſo are you concern'd to honour the Spirit for what he hath done within.— You will honour this Ordinance too, and advantage your ſelves, and you will be inſtrumental to bring in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whoſe hearts are too full of diſguſts and prejudices againſt this high and holy Inſtitution.</p>
               <p>I told you of ſomething I had to ſay to ſinners; I could be well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to ſay nothing at all; had I none at all to ſpeak to. But there are two ranks or ſorts of them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Such as peremptorily (but moſt perniciouſly and erroneouſly) aſſert, that they are above Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, this or that; Sanſ-or ſupra-ordinance men; in what predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to place them, how to call them, or how to cure them I well know not: Is not the Spirit of the Lord ſtraitened? can he do his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:30413:85"/>good by this Ordinance? why then is there no breaking of Bread, no Sacrament of the Lords Supper amongſt you? why is this caſt off, and caſt out? — As the Center of the Earth hath an attractive power and vertue to draw all heavy ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to it; ſo hath the Sacrament ſuch an enlivening, ſtrengthning, nouriſhing power and vertue, as may, nay will draw all real Saints to it; and you amongſt the reſt, if you be ſuch. What is ſaid of <hi>Socrates</hi> is true of the Sacrament, all that know it (its power, preciouſneſs, and uſefulneſs) love it, if any do not love it, it is becauſe they do not know it. The whole management of Soul work in order to Salvation now lies upon the hands of the Spirit, but in the uſe of means. He that made us without us, will not ſave us without us. True it is, means are but means, and therefore not to be relied upon; and as true it is, means are means, and therefore not to be neglected or deſpiſed; 'tis an excellent obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of an eminent Divine: <hi>In
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:30413:86"/>things of this nature men are very prone to run themſelves on one of theſe two rocks;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb</hi> on Rom. 8. <hi>pag.</hi> 246.</note> (ſaith he) <hi>Either they reſt upon the means, not looking up to the Spirit: Or they caſt off the means, caſting all upon the Spirit. Either they are proud and can do all without God; or idle and ſlothful ſo as that God muſt do all without them.</hi> But you ſhould remember that the ſpirits ſole-efficiency (as to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal production of the act) is well enough conſiſtent with mens endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in the uſe of means; he doth all in us and for us, yet he will do nothing without us, nor without means; if he will, you may do well to ſhew where he hath promiſed it, till then we cannot believe it. Our Saviour once though this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance very neceſſary, and he is <hi>the Wiſdom of God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.24.</note> are you wiſer than he? ſpeaking of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, St. <hi>Paul</hi> (moved by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) ſaith, <hi>As often as ye eat this bread, and drink this cup, ye ſhew the Lords Death till he come.</hi> But he
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:30413:86"/>is not yet come, yet you have laid it by as vain, needleſs and fruitleſs.</p>
               <p>Shall his Ordinance have his or your date? He ſet it up, how dare you take it down? You talk much of the Spirit, but ſee and ſay if it be not a ſpirit of pride, or ignor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or a Popiſh ſpirit that prompts you thus to ſpeak and act. They of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church have taken away the Cup, but you have out-done them, in taking away the Bread too. Is the command and example of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt of no force with; ſhall his Inſtitutions be of no longer uſe to, you than your wits and wiſdoms think fit? This Sacrament is <hi>(q.d.)</hi> the picture of our dying Saviour; an injury done to the Kings coyn or picture, is taken as done to the Kings perſon; ſo in this caſe,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Baſil. <hi>de Sp. S. cap.</hi> 28. Gen. 45.3.</note> Men love not to ſee the faces of thoſe they have injured, if arm'd with power to puniſh them.</p>
               <p>How were <hi>Joſephs</hi> Brethren a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed when he ſaid, <hi>I am Joſeph;</hi> what horrour and confuſion will
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:30413:87"/>one day poſſeſs your hearts, when you ſhall hear Chriſt ſay, <hi>I am Jeſus;</hi> I am Jeſus who inſtituted and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed this Ordinance, to continue in full force till the end of the world; I am Jeſus who can and will do you good by my Spirit in the uſe of this Ordinance, if you walk uprightly. But as ſure as I am Jeſus, my enraged juſtice ſhall avenge the quarrel of my abuſed mercy; and they ſhall meet with wrath and vengeance who are contemners of my Ordinance.</p>
               <p>How diſcurſive is fooliſh pride when it would preſcribe unto God? vain man doſt thou cenſure his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits when thou ſhouldſt enjoy them? art thou ſo ſtupid and ſottiſh as to judg of the things conveyed, by the quality and value of the inſtrument that conveys them? Doth not the weakneſs of theſe Elements add much to the wonder of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? It was an argument of Chriſts power to feed five thouſand with a few Loaves; this miracle of
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:30413:87"/>his Sacrament is equal thereunto which feeds the whole Church with ſuch ſlender Elements.— But I will expoſtulate no farther with 'em; I convert my ſpeech to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. For,</p>
               <p n="2">2. As there are ſome who look upon themſelves as above this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, ſo there are others who look upon this Ordinance as above them; and why? but becauſe they are not qualified; nor can any arguments prevail with them to capacitate themſelves for it. Others will ſay, they know no good got by it, no fruit that grows on it. The poor have no leiſure for it, and the rich take no pleaſure in it; and few there are who come to it in moſt Aſſemblies.—I have a word for you, <hi>Et valeat, quantum valere po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Suppoſe this were (but it is not) a prerogative-command, given only for the probation and trial of your obedience, and no benefit at all ſhould redound to the obſerver
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:30413:88"/>of it; are you not (yet) obliged to conſider your ways to turn your feet unto his Teſtimonies; to break off your ſins by repentance, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare your ſelves and then to come and take and eat? The obſervance of ſuch commands hath been well rewarded, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. and the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience thereof moſt ſeverely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; as in <hi>Adam, Gen.</hi> 2.17. in <hi>Lots</hi> wife, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.17. and in the young Prophet.</item>
                  <item>2. Gods ſtanding Laws and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances (and ſuch is this) oblige not to obſervance only, but they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a real benefit withal; which ſhould be an incentive to our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.11. And 119.165. Great peace have they which love and keep thy Law.</item>
                  <item>3. Though you never got good by this Ordinance, will you ſay, no good is to be got by it; or that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any did? it will in no wiſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</item>
                  <item>4. You ſpeak expreſly againſt the Word of God, this very Text; and
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:30413:88"/>for every blaſphemous word you ſhall account another day.</item>
                  <item>5. Do not your ſpeeches reflect upon the glorious Trinity?
<list>
                        <item>1. On God the Father, as if he had made or inſtituted an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in vain; you call in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion his wiſdom.</item>
                        <item>2. On God the Son; as if his Body and Blood were good for nothing. And,</item>
                        <item>3. On this holy Spirit; as if he were ſtraitened ſo, that he could not do them good by it who walk uprightly; or as if he would not.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. Do not you ſpeak againſt the ſweet experience of the Saints in all ages? they have found good by it.</item>
                  <item>7. Do not you ſpeak againſt right reaſon? for as the guilt and danger is great in caſe one receive unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, ſo muſt there in reaſon be ſome proportion of fruit and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to ſuch as come preparedly.</item>
                  <item>8. Once more: Is it not your pride, carnality, and hypocriſie? is
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:30413:89"/>it not your earthlineſs, unbelief and impenitency that hinders your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to it, and proficiency by it? Water there is enough in this well, had you but buckets to draw it forth; the Spirit is preſent to heal, but you are inſenſible of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies. You may complain of us if ſo you will; of God if ſo you dare; of his Decrees, Ordinances, this or that; but aſſure your ſelves, he can as ſoon ceaſe to be God, as ceaſe to be good or juſt; he will lay the fault where you will not like it; whence you ſhall never be able to remove it, even at your own doors. Therefore be adviſed,
<list>
                        <item>1. Cheriſh not any longer ſuch undervaluing thoughts of this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious, holy and precious Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: Judg not raſhly nor falſly of the things of God; I am ſpeaking for God, and for his Inſtitutions; and though it be an eaſie matter to ſlight me your Miniſter, yet I fear, it will be no eaſie province to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer your Maker for the contempt
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:30413:89"/>you do to his ſacred Ordinances.</item>
                        <item>2. Break off your Sins by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and that ſpeedily; though a late repentance may be a true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, yet you will find that a late repentance will prove an hard repentance; a diſeaſe, the longer it grows upon a man the harder it is to be cured. Be quick in this duty, leſt God be quick in judgment, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Repent, or elſe I will come unto thee quickly.</hi>—Mark that quickly.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Lament and weep over your Souls for the loſs of all that good you might ere this day have got by this Ordinance. Now get your perſons clothed with his Righteouſneſs; your natures cleanſed by his Spirit, your ſins pardoned in his blood, and doubt not (if then you come) but the Spirit of the Lord will do you good by this Ordinance. The good Lord follow this work of Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with a work of Converſion. And make this word effectual to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the doubtful; to quicken the ſlotful; to encourage the fearful.
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:30413:90"/>Go to God, though you cannot go in Faith, yet go for Faith; though you cannot, yet he can reform your lifes, and put you into a right frame for communion with him in this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance.</p>
               <p>We are now arrived at the laſt Enquiry.</p>
               <p>Q. 8. <hi>What ſoul-reviving comforts doth this truth afford to the people of God, who care take and conſcience make of walking uprightly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> I will not preſume too far upon your patience, and therefore ſhall not launch out into this vaſt Ocean; take an account of them in theſe ten particulars, and theſe ten rather in Figures, than in words at length. <hi>Is the ſpirit of the Lord at liberty, and has he a ſufficiency of power to enlighten and strengthen, and comfort, and to do you good by this Sacrament?</hi> Here is comfort for you in ten caſes or reſpects.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As to the weakneſs of theſe Sacramental Elements; alas! what is a little morſel of bread, or a ſip of
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:30413:90"/>Wine, and a few words ſpoken over them; (no Tranſubſtantiating words, we abhor all thoughts of that Doctrine which is ſo contrary to our Senſes, to Reaſon, to the Scriptures, to the comfort of the Saints, to the honour of Chriſts glorious Body; all which is abundantly evinced by our Divines.) True it is indeed, they are poor and weak things in themſelves; but you muſt remember they are of divine Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; this is an Ordinance of the great God, who hath own'd it and can and will bleſs it. Though theſe outward Elements be weak, yet the Spirit of the Lord is ſtrong; he delights to do great things by weak means. What is the word, if abſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered, but a dead letter, yet 'tis the power of God unto Salvation to them that believe; 'tis mighty through God, it transforms the heart, reforms the life; by it the dead in ſin are quickened; ſinners are turned from darkneſs unto light; and this is a greater work to turn the Soul from a ſtate of Sin to Grace, than from Grace to Glory. By it Lepers are cleanſed, afflicted Conſciences comforted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What is a little water in Baptiſm to a tender Infant? 'tis in it ſelf but a mean thing; but water-baptiſm is of divine ſanction and inſtitution, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.33. <hi>He that ſent me to Baptize with water;</hi> and Infant-Baptiſm is ſo too, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Go
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:30413:91"/>diſciple ye all Nations:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Poſito toto generali, pars ejus negari non debet.</note> How? <hi>Baptizing them, &amp;c.</hi> and the Spirit of the Lord can do us good by it; yea our tender Infants too, even in their Minority; much more when they arrive at years of Diſcretion. He can and hath made his Elect, who were baptized at ten days, as careful to repent, to believe and obey the Goſpel, as thoſe ever were, who were twenty years of age, ere they were dipped. Say men what they will of it or againſt it, that it is a ſign or ſhadow, this or that; if God ſet us a ſhadow, a brazen Serpent, it ſhall not be in vain to look up unto it. Do not leſs prize or uſe the inſtitution, being well aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd of the Lords Benediction. I told you but even now, That the meanneſs of the Element adds more to the honour and wonder of the Sacrament. And that it derives its being and value from its Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. I refer you for more of this to St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his fourth Book <hi>de Sacr. chap.</hi> 4. <hi>Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 173. And to Biſhop <hi>Reynolds,</hi> his Meditations on the Holy Sacraments, <hi>chap.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2ly.</hi> Here is comfort for you in caſe of bitter taunts and Satyrical or Sarcaſtical ſpeeches which you may meet with from ignorant, ſenſual and ſecure Sinners, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of your conſtant and conſcientious attendance upon God in this Sacred Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſaid long ſince,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:30413:91"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. In all Ages the moſt ſerious holy men are repreſented as the moſt vicious; wicked men have no favour from God, and good men ſhall have no favour from them, whilſt they have virulent Tongues, or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent hands: If the Son of God was crown'd with thorns, let not the Saints of God expect a crown of Roſes: As the Lilly amongſt the Thorns, as the lamb amongſt the Wolves, ſo is the Spouſe amongſt the Daughters. They will do by you as <hi>Stunica</hi> did by <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> obſerve and review all your works, and pick and cull out only what they conceive is worſt; but thoſe perhaps (as did his) may prove your greateſt truths and vertues: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſolace your ſelves in this; The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord is doing you good, and never the leſs for their ſaying or doing you evil; what though you hear ill, whilſt you fare well; their reproaches ſhall hurt you no more, than the Dog does the Moon, which he cannot bite, though he bark all night at it.<note place="margin">Apol. pro Chriſtianis. <hi>Antonin.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Virtus nihil eſt immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuta propter exiſtimationem vulgi. Nobis te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merariae quorundam calumniae ſanctioris vitae inſtitutum non obſcurant, nec per eas gloriae noſtrae coram Deo aliquid decedit;</hi> as <hi>Athena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> told <hi>Antoninus</hi> and <hi>Commodus</hi> in his Apology for the Chriſtians; a Diamond ſparkles never the leſs, nor is it any whit
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:30413:92"/>the leſs precious, becauſe an ignorant or a blind man diſparageth it; 'tis ſo in this caſe; their reproachings tend to your grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter glory; they will wiſh (but perhaps, when 'tis too late) they had been fitted for, admitted to, and ſhared with you in this Sacred Ordinance.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3ly.</hi> Here is matter of comfort for you in reſpect of the meanneſs of the men, or weakneſs of the perſons by whom it is diſpenſed. We are not Prophets, we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to no ſuch inſpirations or immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate calls as they had; we are not Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, we have no immediate call from Chriſt to preach the Goſpel to all Nations; we cannot, do not, dare not pretend to an infallible conduct of the Spirit, as they had, and ſome ignorantly and impudently now challenge to themſelves; No, we are men, men ſubject to like paſſions and perturbations, temptations and infirmities as they were, and perhaps to more than you are; you know it, we confeſs and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it. Guilty were we of ſin before we could do any thing, and ever ſince we could do any thing we have done nothing without ſin. But in this may you and we not little ſolace our ſelves; Though we can do you little good, very little good, yet the Spirit of the Lord can do you very much. All we can do is to endeavour it, but the converſion of Souls is (not ours
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:30413:92"/>but) Gods work; we may (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) ſpeak what is in it ſelf perſwaſive, but 'tis the Spirit of the Lord alone that can and muſt (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) actually perſwade you. The efficacy of the Word and Sacraments de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends not upon the arts, or parts, or gifts, or graces, or greatneſs, or goodneſs of men, but upon the power, inſtitution and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God. Is a golden treaſure ever the worſe becauſe 'tis laid up in an earthen veſſel? or is water the leſs ſweet becauſe conveyed to your ciſterns in leaden pipes? Mark well the Text in hand, and you will find the great ſtreſs laid upon your own upright walking, if you expect a bleſſing; a parallel you have in <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.2. <hi>The word preached did not profit them, not being mixed with faith in them that heard it.</hi> It is not ſaid, <hi>Not being mixed with faith in them that preach it,—but in them that heard it.</hi> In ſhort, the ſpirit of the Lord can do great and mighty things, as by poor and weak means, ſo he can do great and mighty things by poor and weak men. He imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not at the firſt publication of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, any mighty Monarchs, or noble Lords, or profound Philoſophers for the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Nations, whoſe Majeſty, Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Wiſdom might have had a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and prevailing influence on their infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours; No, a few poor Fiſhermen are the men;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.</note> that the excellency of the power
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:30413:93"/>might be and appear to be of God alone, and not in or of man at all: Men and means are productive of nothing if they operate only from an inherent or natural vertue, but when they have a divine ſtamp upon them the Spirit of the Lord can do great and mighty things by them.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4ly.</hi> Here is comfort for you in caſe of temptations to disbelieve the Godhead or Deity of the Holy Ghoſt; other <hi>mediums</hi> are urged to evince his Divinity, but the Ancients make much uſe of this, <hi>viz.</hi> the glorious operations and moſt mighty and powerful works done by him; as <hi>Cyril</hi> and <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>oſtom</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe, de Sp. ſancto.</hi> He that can quicken dead Souls, ſubdue ſuch ſtrong luſts, implant and increaſe Grace, and bleſs the Ordinances, and all this by an immediate primary underived power (as the Spirit doth) certainly he is more than a meer creature, he is truly God; for theſe are works for a God, and for a God only. O the boundleſs, incomprehenſible, and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite power of the Spirit! What all the Creatures yonder above the Clouds with theſe on Earth cannot, that he can do <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipoteutiſſima facilitate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>107.</hi> ad vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talem non procul a fine.</note> as an Ancient ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly expreſſeth it; when he will work, who ſhall let him? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.13. He acts <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotenter, inſuperabiliter,</hi> this ſpeaks him to be God indeed; He is not ſtrained, he can do his people good by his inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:30413:93"/>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5ly.</hi> Here is comfort for you too in caſe of mighty oppoſitions from the fleſh when you are about any holy and religious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes; there is no one duty in the whole courſe of Chriſtianity, but it is ſure to meet with one impediment or other. The Fleſh (if nothing elſe do) wil beluſting againſt the Spirit, corruption will be oppoſing grace; ſo that you cannot do the things that you would and ſhould: The agency and enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the fleſh appears both in the matter and manner of our performances. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it hinders from duty, from praying, hearing, and receiving, ſometimes in duty; nay it ever hinders us in the manner; aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the vigor and fervour, or leſſening the alacrity of our Souls in duty, your own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience is proof ſufficient; but here is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for you in this preſent caſe, the Spirit of the Lord is not ſhortned, nor ſtraitned, he can help your infirmities, ſubdue corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions quicken graces, and in ſpite of all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions he can bleſs his own Inſtitutions: He can make mountains to become plains, and cut a way through the hard rock, <hi>Zach</hi> 4.9. <hi>Behold I am the Lord, the God of all fleſh, is there any thing too hard for me?</hi> Jer. 32.27. It may, poor Soul, be too hard for thee, but not for me; this is applicable to the Spirit in the perſonal conſideration of God, and it is no leſs comfortable than ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable.</p>
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:30413:94"/>
               <p>A Child of God fain would do more but cannot; a wicked man may do more but will not; the godly mans heart is larger than the duties; a wicked mans duties are larger than his heart; 'tis the complaint of a gracious Soul, O how do my corruptions hinder in theſe holy duties! But O, ſays the other, how do theſe duties hinder me in the purſuit of my luſts!</p>
               <p>A godly man is griev'd becauſe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do all the good that he would; and the other, becauſe he cannot do all the evil that he would. 'Tis the burden of a Saint, the greateſt trouble upon his Spirit, that he can pray no more fervently, hear no more profitably, receive no more worthily; ſo to bungle and baffle, and trifle, is his great trouble; but he hath this to comfort him, The good Spirit of the Lord to aſſiſt and help him in every duty; and he knows, that his arm is not ſhortned.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6ly.</hi> Here is comfort for you as in caſe of the activeneſs of the fleſh, ſo in caſe of the weakneſs of the Spirit; <hi>i.e.</hi> of Grace; you find that you are wofully and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſtraitned in your ſelves; you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the narrowneſs of your Hearts, the unactiveneſs of Grace, you are not ſo hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and holy, not ſo tender-hearted and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged; your lives are nothing ſo blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and harmleſs as you could wiſh, and this to you is matter of ſaddeſt Lamentation
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:30413:94"/>and deepeſt Humiliation. But remember (pray) the Spirit of the Lord is not ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, though you be, he is not; and this is matter of conſolation; though you be impotent, chill and dull; yet if you be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of it, and ſorrowful for it, you will find his Grace ſufficient for you, and himſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient in you: A weak Chriſtian aſſiſted by the Spirit of the Lord can do all things, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7ly.</hi> Here is comfort for you againſt thoſe oppoſitions and temptations you may meet with from the Devil when you are at the Lords Table: O that we were as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to prepare our ſelves for that Ordinance as he is to prepare for us; he is ever fixed, and very diligent on holy days, in holy pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, at holy duties, <hi>Job</hi> 1.6. not becauſe he loves them, but becauſe he hates us. I have read of one who ſaid, he ſaw but one De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil in the Market, for moſt of the buyers and ſellers were his already; but a Legion in the Church; A Legion (according to <hi>Varro</hi>) is 7622; but what imploy had ſo many evil ſpirits there? why, to lay ſnares for them; to hinder the operation of the Word and Sacraments, and conſequently the ſalvation of Souls. Doubtleſs you are not without diſcouragements by reaſon of your own corruptions, and his oppoſitions. Well but your Redeemer hath not left you comfortleſs; the Spirit of the Lord is not
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:30413:95"/>ſtraitned; He is a moſt glorious and victorious Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; your way in this caſe is, to ſet the power of this Spirit againſt the power of Satan; when the gates of Hell, and powers of Darkneſs preſs hard upon you, 'tis your wiſdom (in order to your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and conqueſt) to improve this power of the Spirit of the Lord. The more you are aſſaulted by that evil ſpirit, the more ſhall you be aſſiſted by this good ſpirit. He will be with you in the floods and in the flames; Who and what art thou O great Mountain before this <hi>Zerubbabel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8ly.</hi> Here is comfort for you as to the greatneſs of thoſe mercies and bleſſings now by you deſired and expected. O ſays a child of God, how ſhall I get my heart humble, more quick and lively; what ſhall I do for a broken, bleeding. Heart, for more full aſſurance of the pardon of my ſin, and the ſalvation of my Soul. Ah what ſhall, poor I do for a little more light in my Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; O that my Will were healed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are great things, they are not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, no, they are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſuch as accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany Salvation.</hi> Yet although theſe be very great things as to you, they are not ſo to the Spirit of the Lord, if it be marvelous in your eyes, is it therefore marvelous in Gods? <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.6. All things are alike eaſie to an Almighty Agent, and this Spirit is ſuch;<note place="margin">Exod. 14.24.</note> a look from him in anger can lay your ſtrongeſt luſts dead; he can irradiate your minds with beams of Divine light; and efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly incline, overpower, determine and heal your<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Wills. He can (in one word) do every thing; therefore be confident of this very thing; <hi>viz.</hi> that as he eaſily can, ſo he aſſuredly will. He, I ſay, who hath begun a good work in you, will own it and crown it and perform it until the day of Chriſt, <hi>Job</hi> 42.2. with <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.6.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9ly.</hi> Here is alſo comfort for you in caſe of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs under former adminiſtrations; perhaps you find not that power as yet over your impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous luſts as you then and there expected; no
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:30413:95"/>more peace of conſcience; <hi>Nec mibi dant ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>llae lucem, &amp;c.</hi> You have often been at the Lords Table, and yet no aſſurance, or no more aſſurance of his love, and of eternal life, than you had before. If it be thus your preſent caſe is ſad; yet thus it may be, &amp; your internal &amp; eternal ſtate be good. For though you have not peace, yet you want not grace, in the beſt of Saints there is a want in grace, but in the worſt or weakeſt Saint there is not a want of grace. Though you are caſt down, yet you are not caſt off; you have not ſo much as will comfort you, but you have enough to ſave you. 'Tis Heaven that is the proper place of comfort, and Earth of grace: 'Tis the pleaſure of our all-wiſe God to make ſome to weep and wait long for a ſmile from Heaven; and thus he acts in a way of wiſdom, not ever in a way of puniſhment. Know and do your own work, let the moſt High alone with his; hear what he will ſpeak for he will ſpeak peace unto his people; the day that's clouded now may be clear anon; 'tis darkeſt a little before the dawning of the day. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member for your comfort,<note place="margin"> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Lux fidei, veritatis, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>materia perpetuae laetitiae: Orta Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa; juſti multa pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur, ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam laeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ fruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> that light is ſown for the Righteous, and joy for the upright in heart, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 97.11. The Interval of time may be conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble between the ſowing and the reaping. But act you faith on the Promiſes, acquieſce in and ſubmit to the Will and Wiſdom of the Lord; for unto the Upright (and they are the perſons I am now ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing this diſcourſe to) I ſay, unto the upright there ariſeth light in darkneſs; <hi>i.e.</hi> comfort in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; remember that the Spirit of the Lord is not ſtraitned. Concerning him take three notions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with you: He is</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>A free Agent;</hi> as the wind bloweth when and where it lifteth, ſo the Spirit worketh, witneſſeth, ſealeth &amp; aſſureth when &amp; whom himſelf pleaſeth.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>A wiſe Agent;</hi> and therefore will act moſt ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably and opportunely, when it will moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to his own honour and your comfort.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>A ſtrong and mighty Agent;</hi> when he begins 'tis
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:30413:96"/>not ſin, nor Satan, nor the World ſhall let him: Therefore though now you mourn, yet you may not murmur; Groan you may, but muſt not grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, be it never ſo little life &amp; light, and power and peace you have arrived at. I ſay to you as did <hi>Elibis</hi> to <hi>Job,</hi> ch. 34.32. ſhould it be according to your mind? is it fit you have juſt what you will, and when you will; if you will be your own car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, take heed of cutting your own fingers. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw not from this Ordinance; but (as before) wait with patience and work with diligence; for the Spirit of the Lord is not ſtraitned; this is a reviving Cordial in this caſe.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> an Heathen Philoſopher deſired no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Heathen gods ſo much as the Spirit of <hi>Socrates.</hi> You have a more glorious Spirit, this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord, who will in due time make you more fruitful and cheerful; and give you more increaſe of grace, more ſetled peace of Conſcience; yea an abſolute maſtery and victory over all your ſpiritual enemies. Once more, and I diſmiſs you.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10ly.</hi> This ſpeaks comfort to you who perſevere in prayer; the ſeed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> not in name only (as were theſe in the Text) but in deed and truth.</p>
               <p>To hold on in Duty is not the practice of the moſt,<note place="margin">Job 27.10</note> but of the beſt; 'tis no eaſie work which is both above nature and againſt it: This affords comfort to you; 'tis like the rod of myrtle in the travellers hand,<note place="margin">Pliny.</note> which makes him freſh and lively, and keeps him from being weary; O nouriſh no jealous thoughts of God; if you diſtruſt him, you will deſert him.</p>
               <p>Remember for your encouragement and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that the good Spirit of the Lord is in full power, and at liberty ſtill to give a bleſſing by, as at the firſt to give a being to his holy Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>To which ever-bleſſed Spirit, together with the Father and the Son, be aſcrib'd all Honour and Glory, World without end..</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="185" facs="tcp:30413:96"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
